翻譯： @塔拉Tala
"Piano Concerto  in A Minor Op. 54-1"]
The only thing  I ever knew was cotton.
我以前只知道一件事，那就是棉花
It was hard work.
這是一項非常辛苦的工作
Now, you know cotton is ready  when the bud splits,
此時，當棉鈴裂開時就意味著棉花已經成熟了
and the boll is star-shaped,
棉球是星形的
like a big 0l' star in the sky.
如同是鑲嵌在夜空中一顆古老的星星.
Or like your big 0l' head.
或者就像是你的大腦袋.
Hold on, is that some cotton?
等等, 那是棉花嗎?
Is that cotton?
那是個棉花嗎?
But I didn't mind,
但我從不在意,
'cause I got to spend all day  working with my daddy.
因為我可以一整天都和爸爸在一起幹活兒
- Hurry, take this picture.  - Take a picture of y'all.
- 快點, 拍張照片.  - 為你們所有人拍張照片.
Why don't everybody smile?
為什麼大家都那麼嚴肅?
Teeth.
露出牙齒.
Hattie, come on,  I need your help in the shed.
哈蒂, 過來  到小屋裏幫我一下
Come on.
過來.
- Pa... where he taking Ma?  - Get back to work.
- 爸爸，他帶媽媽去哪兒?  - 快回去幹活
Cecil, come back here, boy.
塞西爾, 回來這裏.
Mama!
媽媽!
Come here.
過來.
Look at me, boy.
看著我, 孩子.
Don't you lose your temper  with that man.
不要跟那個男人爭論.
This his world.  We just living in it.
這是他的地盤兒  我們只是住在這裏而已
You hear me?
聽明白了嗎?
Now, get on back to work.
那麼，現在快回去幹活兒吧.
Pa, what you gonna do?
爸爸，你準備怎麼辦?
H9)'-
喂.
' Dad!
爸爸!
- [gunshoq
Oh, my Lord.
噢，上帝呀.
Who you looking at?! Huh?
你看誰呢?! 啊?
Who wants to go next?!  You get back to work.
還有誰不想活了?!  回去幹活兒.
Hey, you. Get some of the hands  to help dig a hole for his pa.
喂, 你. 去找幾個人挖個坑把他爸爸給埋了
Hurry UP!
快點!
Stop crying-
不要哭了.
I'm gonna have you  in the house now.
現在我要帶你去房子裏.
I'm gonna teach you  how to be a house nigger.
我會教你成為一名會做屋內服務的黑鬼
- He's coming.  - Yes'm.
- 他來了.  - 好的，夫人.
And quiet when you're serving.
上菜的時候最好不要出聲.
I don't even want  to hear you breathe.
最好連呼吸聲都不要讓我聽到.
Yes, ma'am.
是對, 夫人.
The room should feel  empty when you're in it.
你待在房間裏的時候要形同空氣.
It was much nicer working  in the house than in the field.
在房間裏幹活兒要比在地裏幹活舒適得多.
Crazy nigger, from the left.
你這個愚蠢的黑鬼, 要記得從左邊開始.
Give me more.
多給我一點兒.
Hmm.
嗯.
When I got older, I knew  I had to go before he killed me, too.
我的年紀一天天在長大，我開始意識到  我一定得在他殺了我之前離開.
Part of me was scared to leave.
但與此同時，我卻又害怕離開那裏.
It was the only world I ever knew.
因為我從未離開過那個地方.
Ma, I took Pa's watch.
媽媽, 我帶著爸爸的手錶.
Ma?
媽媽?
Ma, I'm leaving.
媽媽，我要走了.
My mama never  spoke much after that.
那次事件之後，我媽媽開始變得沉默寡言.
I knew she'd miss me,
我知道她會想念我,
but I also knew she wanted me  to leave that place.
但是我也知道她希望我離開那個地方.
And even though  Miss Annabeth never said it,
還有，儘管安娜貝絲小姐對我的離開  從未講過隻言片語
I knew she'd miss me, too.
但是我知道她也一樣會想念我.
I don't think God meant  for people to not have a family.
我不覺得上帝是有意想要拆散一個家庭
Outside the cotton fields was even worse  than I thought it would be.
棉花田以外的世界遠遠比我想像得還要糟糕許多.
No one would give me a job  nor food nor a place to sleep.
沒有人願意給我提供工作的機會  更不用說食物和睡覺的地方
Any white man could kill  any of us at any time
任何一個白人都有可能隨時隨地殺掉我們
and not be punished for it.
而且不用擔心遭受懲罰.
The law wasn't on our side.
那時的法律不僅不會保護我們.
The law was against us.
而且....對我們很不利
I was hungry all the time.
每天我都飢腸轆轆
You know what can happen  to you, son?
孩子，你知道這樣做的後果會是什麼，對嗎?
Get up.
起來.
I said, get up.
我說了，起來.
I'm gonna have to lie  to the boss man about that window.
那個窗戶的事，我必須得跟老闆撒謊
The good Lord say  we ain't supposed to lie.
可是上帝說我們不應該撒謊.
Sorry, sir.
對不起，先生.
Where's your ma and your pa?
你爸爸和媽媽在哪兒?
My ma crazy in the head,  and my pa got killed.
我媽媽的精神有點不正常  我爸爸被殺了
I'll make you  some ham sandwiches
我給你做幾個火腿三明治
and send you on your way.
然後送你出去
The boss will be here  in a minute.
老闆馬上就到了
Sunday's our busiest morning.
星期天的早晨是我們最忙的時間.
You looking for some help?  I know how to serve.
你需要幫手嗎?  我知道該如何伺候顧客.
You done broke our window,  you done stole our food,
你打碎了我們的窗戶，還偷了我們的食物,
and now you asking for a job?
然後你還想在這裏工作?
Back in Macon,  I'm a house nigger, a good one.
在梅肯的時候,我是個做屋內服務的黑鬼  我做得很不錯
Don't you ever use that word, son.
不要再用黑鬼那個詞了，知道了嗎，孩子
That's the white man's word.
那是白人的詞
It's filled With hate.
那個詞充滿了敵意
Didn't your father  ever teach you any better?
難道你爸爸沒有教過你嗎?
- Slow down.  - Yes, sir.
- 慢一點.  - 是，先生.
You got to look through their eyes.
你要學會看眼色.
See what it is they want.
通過他們的顏色就能知道他們需要什麼
- Got it?  - Strokes.
- 明白了嗎?  - 嗯，動作要很輕
- Yeah, I got it.  - Here.
- 是的，我明白了.  - 給你.
See what it is they need.
看看他們需要什麼.
Right this way.
這邊請.
Anticipate.
預測.
I'm sorry. I'm sorry, ma'am.
對不起，對不起，女士.
Bring a smile to the eyes...
要盡可能地讓你的服務對像...
...of your principal.
露出微笑
Perfect. Perfect.
完美，非常完美
Don't forget to save me them chitlins.
別忘了給我留一些豬腸.
- Why you like chitlins so much?  - 'Cause they're good eating.
- 為什麼你那麼喜歡豬腸?  - 因為豬腸很好吃.
The manager of Excelsior, in DC,  he came by yesterday.
華盛頓Excelsior酒店的經理昨天正好路過這裏
He offered me a job as a butler.
他給我提供了一份男僕的工作
He must be paying you  top dollar, huh, boss?
他肯定會付你最高的薪水吧，老闆?
Yeah.
嗯.
I was thinking about taking it,  but I don't know.
我正琢磨著要不要接受那份工作  我還不確定
I'm too old to be leaving  North Carolina.
我已經太老了，現在離開北卡羅來納州  怕是不太合適
I'm just fine right here.
我在這裏待著也很不錯.
I told him to hire you.
我已經向他推薦了你.
I'm just now finding my way  around this hotel.
現在這家酒店，我也才剛剛摸出點門道
Ain't ready for all them  highfalutin white people,
還不足以去應付所有那些傲慢的白人,
all their fancy words.
還有他們的那些花哨的言辭
ours,
塞西爾, 我們都有兩張面孔:  一張是我們自己的,
and the ones that we got  to show the white folks.
另一張則是我們給那些白人看的.
Now, to get up in the world,
現在，你想要在這個世界上立足
you have to make  them feel nonthreatened.
你一定不能讓他們感覺到有威脅.
Use that, them fancy words  that I've taught you.
要學會使用我教過你的那些花哨的言語
White folks up north,  they like some uppity coloreds.
北方的那些白人們  他們喜歡傲慢的有色人種
Yeah.
是的.
I took that job  up in Washington, DC.
我接受了華盛頓的那份工作.
It was the most beautiful hotel  I'd ever seen.
那是我所見過的最漂亮的酒店
I hope it wasn't  too presumptuous of me
在你們經歷了從布法羅到華盛頓
to have prepared a few spirits
如此漫長的旅程之後,我希望我為你們準備的
after your long journey here  from Buffalo.
這兩杯酒不會太冒昧
The best decision that court ever  made was to slow this whole mess down.
法院有史以來作過的做好的決定  就是延緩了這場亂糟糟的烏龍事件
Nigger boys in school with white girls.  Who ever heard of such a thing?
讓黑鬼小子和白人女孩們在同一所學校上學  有誰聽說過比這更荒唐的事?
Next thing you know,  they'd be fornicating.
要真發生那樣的事，那麼接下來的事情  就會是黑人和白人開始通姦
Gentlemen, this here is different.  We could start another Civil War.
先生們, 現在的情形不同了  我們可以發動另一場內戰.
Cecil, what do you think about niggers  going to school with white children?
塞西爾, 你對於黑鬼和白人小孩在同一所學校就讀  的事有何看法?
To be honest with you,  Mr. Jenkins,
跟你說實話, 詹金斯先生
I tend to not be too concerned
我不是太關心美國的政治
with American or European politics.
或者歐洲的政治.
Nor should you, Cecil.  They're all criminals.
你的確也不應該關心, 塞西爾.  他們都是些罪犯
Earl Warren should be shot  and hanged.
厄爾·沃倫應該被槍決或者處以絞刑
That dumb son-of-a-bitch judge  is trying to integrate our schools.
那個婊子養的傻X法官居然想要整合我們的學校  （指取消美國學校的種族隔離制度）
I think Judge Warren is going to find  that quite challenging.
我想沃倫法官會發現執行這一裁決  將會面臨巨大的挑戰.
Damn right, Cecil. Damn right.
太對了, 塞西爾.你說得太對了.
Never in my life did I dream  I'd work in a place as fancy as this.
我以為從未夢想過我會在如此奢華的地方工作.
I never dreamed my life  could be so good.
我從未夢想過我會擁有如此棒的生活.
Gloria and I met working  at the Excelsior.
我和格羅瑞亞是在Excelsior酒店  一起工作時認識的.
She was a maid at the hotel,
那是她在酒店裏做女僕,
but now her only job  was raising our two boys.
但是現在，她唯一的工作就是  養育和照顧我們的兩個兒子
I made sure that they  never laid eyes on a cotton field.
我很確定他們從不知道棉花田是個什麼東東.
- I got to pee.  - Not today. Don't try that.
- 我要去尿尿.  - 今天不行，別在琢磨花招了.
- Finish that homework.  - Where Louis at?
- 快點把作業寫完.  - 路易斯在哪兒?
- He's taking the trash out.  - Working late again?
- 他去丟垃圾了.  - 又工作到這麼晚?
- How was your shift?  - Beats working for a living.
- 值夜班感覺怎麼樣?  - 比上白班輕鬆多了.
I miss you at night, honey.
晚上我很想你，親愛的.
Didn't you say you got to pee?  Go on, then.
你剛不是說你要去尿尿嗎，那麼快去吧
Wash your hands when you come  out of that bathroom, boy.
從洗手間出來的時候要記得洗手，小子.
- Good morning.  - Good morning.
- 早上好.  - 早上好.
Good morning, sir.
早上好，先生.
Mm-hm.
- Hey, Dad.  - Hey, Louis.
- 嗨，爸爸.  - 嗨，路易斯.
- You all right?  - Yeah, I'm fine.
- 你還好嗎?  - 嗯，我很好.
- Good.  - That woman whose son got killed,
- 那很好.  - 兒子被別人殺了的那個女人
she's around doing speeches now.  What's her name, honey?
她正在四處發表演講呢.  她叫什麼名字來著?
- Mamie Till.  - Mamie...
- 瑪米 提爾.  - 瑪米...
Mamie Till. Mm.
瑪米 提爾， 嗯
I remember that story just  like it was yesterday,
那事兒雖然都已經過去三年了
even though it was three years ago.
可感覺就好像是昨天才發生的一樣
It was a dis-damn-grace  what they did to that boy.
那簡直就TMD是一種恥辱  他們對那個男孩子所做的那一切.
Just for looking at a white woman.
就只是為了尋找一個白人女人而已.
Beat him up,
他們把他打個半死,
threw his body in the river,  killed him.
還把他丟到河裏，淹死了他.
He wasn't no older than Louis.  He was 14 at the time.
他死的時候只有14歲，  還沒路易斯大呢
- Crazy white folks down South.  - Thanks, Ma.
- 那些瘋狂的白人南蠻子.  - 謝謝，媽媽.
At least we got it  a little better in DC, huh?
起碼我們在華盛頓  處境要稍稍好一點，對吧?
Still treating us bad, too.
對待我們也一樣很糟糕.
Get on down here, Charlie!  Wash your hands.
快過來這裏, 查理!  把你的手洗了.
Louis said we should stop  taking the white man's shit.
路易斯說我們不應該再繼續忍受那些白人的欺負了.
- Hey.  - Shut up.
- 喂.  - 閉嘴.
- Watch your mouth.  - Watch your mouth.
- 注意你的言辭.  - 注意你的言辭.
Hello, Gaines' residence.
你好, 這裏是蓋恩斯家.
Uh, yeah. Hold on, Mr. Kidgan.
嗯，對，稍等, 凱根先生.
- It's the boss man, Dad.  - What's he calling for?
- 是你老闆，爸爸.  - 他打電話來有什麼事?
When the white man call,  I always assume the worst.
每當白人打電話來的時候,  我總是會做最壞的打算.
Yes, sir?
你好，先生
I would have put money on it
我總是覺得那天
that I was getting laid off  or something that day.
我可能會被解雇，或者其他的類似的事情.
- Would you follow me, please?  - Yes, sir.
- 請跟我來  - 好的.
I'm Cecil Gaines.
我是塞西爾 蓋恩斯
- It's a pleasure to meet you.  - You, as well.
- 很高興見到你.  - 我也一樣.
Have a seat.
請坐.
Are you political, Mr. Gaines?
你參與政治活動嗎, 蓋恩斯先生?
- No, sir.  - Good.
- 沒有，先生.  - 那很好.
We have no tolerance  for politics at the White House.
在白宮，我們不會容忍任何與政治有關的事情.
- How'd you find me?  - I didn't.
- 你是怎麼找到我的?  - 我沒有找你.
You served R.D. Warner  at the Excelsior Hotel.
你在 Excelsior 酒店的時候曾為R.D.沃納先生服務過.
He oversees operations  for the entire White House.
他負責整個白宮的運營事務.
- You made quite an impression.  - I don't recall.
- 你給他留下了很深刻的印象.  - 我不記得了.
Mr. Warner and myself make note  of potential staff around town.
沃納和我一直在為白宮留意和挖掘  一些比較有潛力的員工.
Butler positions rarely open,
男僕這個職位很少會空缺,
as most stay on for 3O years or more.
因為大部分男僕都會在這個職位上  待30年甚至更久.
I know I was quite surprised  when I got the call.
我接到電話的時候非常驚訝.
It was a surprise  for me, as well.
我也覺得很驚訝.
As the White House maTtre d',  I normally hire the butlers.
作為白宮的總管,  男僕這個職位通常是由我來負責招聘的
Forgive me for saying this,  Mr. Fallows.
法洛斯先生，原諒我這麼說...
I certainly wouldn't want to  be hired under circumstances
如果僱傭我會讓你覺得不太舒服
that would make you  feel uncomfortable.
那麼我也不想在這種情況下接受這份工作
Oh, really?
噢，真的嗎?
You need butlers  that you've handpicked,
你需要一名你精心挑選的男僕
men to your liking  that will fulfill your vision
一個各方面都能讓你
of a proper White House staff.
稱心如意的員工.
Hmm.
嗯
Is that... Louis XIII?
那是... 路易十三?
These decanters are replicas
那些酒瓶是在雅爾納克戰場上
of metal flasks that were found  on the battlefield in Jarnac.
找到的那些金屬酒壺的復製品
Correct?
對嗎?
The Italians, they  know their wines,
意大利人很懂他們的葡萄酒
and the Irish, they certainly know  how to make a great whiskey.
至於愛爾蘭人, 他們也非常明白  如何才能釀製出上好的威士忌
But I believe the French  have a distinct advantage
但是我相信法國人在釀製干邑白蘭地方面
when it comes to Cognac.
有著獨特的優勢
(Test vrai?
我說得對嗎?
Yeah, you'll make  a good house nigger.
嗯，你會成為一名很好的黑鬼僕人.
Would you care  for a demitasse?
要不要來杯咖啡?
Sometimes it just be  me and Faye up in here.
有時候我和法耶會待在這裏.
Me, Faye  and a little scotch.
我，法耶，還有一點點威士忌.
Have a good time.
祝你玩得愉快.
That's how you do it.
你總是做的很棒.
You know how to throw  a bash, girl.
你知道如何成功地舉辦一場舞會
What did you do  to this potato salad?
這個土豆沙拉你是怎麼弄的?
I'll tell you what I did.  I put some dill in it,
我來告訴你我是怎麼做的吧  我在沙拉裏放了一點小茴香
because I read in Woman's Day,  where pickles drown out the flavor
那是我在婦女日報上看到的  上面說酸黃瓜會蓋掉其他味兒
and dill bring up the flavor.
而茴香則會提味兒.
- That's what you tasting right now.  - OK. Yeah.
- 你現在吃的就是那個加了茴香的東東  - 好吧.
- I like it.  - Make a difference, don't it?
- 我很喜歡.  - 跟以前有點點區別，對吧?
It really does.
還真是那麼回事.
Girl, you must be so proud of Cecil.
塞西爾肯定讓你感到特別驕傲吧.
You know he got that job hisself.  The White House called him,
你知道，他是靠自己的本事贏得了那份工作  是白宮打電話來找的他
- he didn't call the White House.  - He's a good man.
- 而不是他打過電話給白宮.  - 他是個很好的男人
- You got a good man.  - She's fun, man!
- 你嫁了個好男人.  - 她很開心呀!
Not like this one right here.  OI' sourpuss.
而不像是坐在這裏的這位壞脾氣的嘮叨婆
- You still mad at me?  - I got reason.
- 你還在生我的氣嗎?  - 我生氣是有原因的.
No, you don't. I told you,  I went down to the numbers spot,
不，你沒理由生氣啦，我已經跟你講了  我去了那個玩紙牌的地方
played my little numbers,  got me some barbecue,
玩了會兒牌, 吃了點燒烤,
and then I went down...  I didn't even get nothing to drink!
然後，我又去了...  我真的什麼都沒喝!
I am so... I'm so sick of these  numbers spot stories, Howard.
我很煩... 我很煩再聽你說什麼打牌的故事，霍華德
How you expect me to believe you  was down at the numbers spot?
你怎能指望我還會相信你
Whether you believe it  or not don't mean it ain't true.
你信，或者不信  事實就擺在那裏
- Come on, stop this mess.  - You want to do this right now?
- 好啦，別再吵了  - 你真的想現在吵架麼
Come on, y'all.  Come on, come on, come on.
行啦，你們倆個, 行啦，行啦
You don't believe it, you don't  have to believe it, but...
你愛信不信，你也用不著相信  但是...
- Come on, y'all.  - Such a shuckster.
- 行啦，你們兩個.  - 大騙子.
- You really want to do this right now?  - Stop this right now.
- 你真的想挑這個時候吵架麼?  - 都馬上給我閉嘴.
You need to pick on  somebody your own size.
你總得找個個頭和你差不多的人比劃吧
We are here to celebrate,  so y'all could be nice just one time.
我們在這裏是為了慶祝塞西爾的新工作的,  所以你們兩個能不能好好的哪怕就這一次也行.
You heard the lady.  Come on, get over here, let's celebrate!
你聽到她說的話了吧  來吧，過來讓我們慶祝慶祝
Celebrate.
慶祝
That's why I was out,  trying to make you happy.
那就是為什麼我要出去的原因  我是為了讓你開心嘛
- Y'all need to get a room.  - What? What?
- 你們倆需要找個房間吧.  - 什麼，什麼啦?
Ain't that the truth?  Or something.
難道不是嗎
He drives me crazy. He just... Ugh!
他都快把我逼瘋了.  他... !
You ain't, uh...  You want to come to the room with us?
你, 嗯... 你想跟我們一起進去嗎?
No.
不.
- Hey, where the boys at?  - They upstairs in the back room.
- 喂，其他孩子在哪兒?  - 他們在樓上後面的房間.
Boys! Get on down here!  I need to see your face now!
小伙子們，下來這裏吧!  讓我看看你們!
- What y'all doing up there?  - Yes, congratulations.
- 你們在上面幹嘛呢?  - 祝賀你.
Honey, when you gonna take me  to the White House?
親愛的,你打算什麼時候帶我去白宮瞧瞧?
You want to go  to the White House, baby?
你想去白宮, 寶貝?
You know I want to go  to the White House.
你知道我想去白宮.
When you want to go?
那你想什麼時候去?
- Don't play with me now...  - When you want to go?
- 別跟我瞎逗了...  - 你想什麼時候去?
The White House,  now that's a big step up.
白宮,那可是一個很大的進步.
- Ooh!  - Yeah, it's exciting.
- 哇!  - 對，讓我很興奮.
Girl, you up in that house now!  I want to hear all the stories.
姑娘們，大家都去樓上吧!  我想聽聽所有的故事.
I don't know how many stories  you gonna hear,
我可不曉得你究竟想聽多少故事,
'cause they done swore him  to some kind of secret code,
因為他們已經讓他宣過誓
- and he can't tell me nothing.  - No. Girl, you give it to him right.
- 他什麼都不能跟我透漏.  - 不會的，姑娘，只要你把他服侍好.
- Mm-hm! He'll tell you everything.  - That's the key right there.
- 他會告訴你一切的.  - 這就是關鍵.
You listening?
你聽到了嗎?
- Did you hear her?  - Who you been giving it to?
- 你聽到她說什麼了嗎?  - 那你都服侍誰來著?
Well, if you was at home,  I could be giving it to you.
這個嘛，如果你一直待在家裏  我服侍的那個人必然就是你.
I don't know  what you talking about.
我不知道你們在說什麼.
Boys, y'all better bring  y'all little narrow butts down here!
小伙子們，你們最好把你們的瘦屁股挪到樓下來!
- Here they come.  - Called y'all 19 times.
- 他們來了.  - 都叫你們800遍了.
Boys, stop running through this house.  You know better than that.
小伙子們，別在房間裏四處亂竄.  你們懂的.
Elroy! Get over here.  Come here.
埃爾羅伊! 過來這裏
Give me some money.
給我點兒錢.
Nah. Tell them... Tell them what  you gonna be when you grow up.
告訴他們... 告訴他們等你長大了你準備幹什麼.
I want to work at the White  House just like Mr. Gaines.
我想要跟蓋恩斯先生一樣在白宮工作.
- Ah, that's my boy.  - Right there.
- 噢，那才是我兒子.  - 對.
All right, man.
好吧.
Louis! What you gonna be  when you grow up?
路易斯! 等你長大了你想幹什麼?
You gonna work at  the White House like your daddy?
你也想像你爸爸一樣在白宮工作嗎?
- I don't know.  - I'll tell you one thing.
- 我不知道.  - 我跟你說一件事吧.
I knew exactly what I wanted  to be when I was 13.
我13歲的時候我就已經非常確切地知道了我的理想.
Yeah, a number runner.
對, 要做一個賭棍.
I'm Cecil Gaines.  I'm the new butler.
我是塞西爾 蓋恩斯  我是新來的男僕
Yes, sir.
是的，先生.
There are 16 full-time maids.
那裏有16位全職的女僕.
We have six butlers,  four carpenters, two painters,
我們有六位男僕  四位是木匠，兩位是油漆匠
seven electricians,  three dishwashers, three doormen,
七位電工,三位洗碗工, 三位門衛,
a full kitchen staff, including pastry  chef and three full-time calligraphers.
一位全職的廚房職工，兼任糕點師傅  還有三位全職的謄寫員.
Two painters, seven  electricians, nine engineers...
兩位油漆匠, 七位電工, 九位機修工...
Here comes Warner.
沃納來了.
Uh, Mr. Warner, wanted to thank you  for the opportunity
沃納先生, 我想謝謝你給我這個..
to work in the White House...
在白宮工作的機會...
Come on. Here we go.
算了，我們走吧.
Ma'am, I'm Cecil Gaines.  I'll be working with you here.
夫人，我是塞西爾 蓋恩斯  我會在這裏與您一起工作.
Mr. Gaines,  please don't do that.
蓋恩斯先生,請不要那麼做.
- Come on.  - Yes, sir.
- 走吧.  - 是的，先生.
Now, when lifting a plate,  never scrape the bottom.
端盤子的時候一定要小心不要刮花盤子點底部
Never listen  or react to conversation.
永遠不要留意他們的談話或者作出任何反應
- The room should feel as...  - Empty when I'm in it.
- 你待在房間裏的時候...  - 要做到形同空氣.
So then she says...
所以他們說...
Then she says, "Stick..."
所以他們說, "伸出來... "
"CK-"
"好 "
Then she starts  screaming and yells,
然後她開始尖叫,
"Stick your whole hand in!"  So I put my whole hand in.
"把你的整個手伸進去!"  所以我就把整個手伸進去.
Then she yells out,  "Put both hands in!"
然後她又開始大叫,  "要用兩隻手!"
"OK!"
"好的!"
Then she screams,  "Now clap!"
然後她又叫, "現在，拍手!"
I say, "I can't."
我說, "我不能. "
She looks up, smiles and says,
她仰起頭，笑著說,
"See, I told you my..."
"你瞧, 我跟你說了我的... "
That ain't funny.
那一點兒都不好笑.
Hey, there he is!  Heard you were coming.
噢，他在這裏!  我聽說你要來
- What's your name?  - Cecil.
- 你叫什麼名字?  - 塞西爾
- Cecil Gaines.  - That ain't funny.
- 塞西爾 蓋恩斯  - 那不好笑.
I'm Carter Wilson, head butler.  Don't worry about Big Mo behind you.
我是卡特 威爾遜，這裏的首席男僕.  別擔心你身後的那個大塊頭.
That brother will steal your wallet  before you even knew it.
那哥們會趁你不注意到時候偷走你的錢包.
This brother in the mirror over here,  his name's James Holloway.
你從鏡子裏可以看到的那哥們  他叫詹姆斯 霍洛威
- He's my second in command.  - James.
- 他是我的第二把手.  - 詹姆斯.
Jackie Robinson or Willie Mays?
你是傑克 羅賓森還是威利 梅斯?
Why don't you shake  the man's hand first
為什麼你不能在開始問你那些刁鑽問題之前
before you start asking difficult  questions like that?
先跟這哥們握個手?
I just want to know  where the man's coming from.
我只是想知道他是打哪兒來的.
Look like the jury's still  out on that one, right?
看上去還沒有得出結論，對嗎?
Welcome.  Fancy Freddie give you the tour yet?
歡迎你. 范希 弗雷迪已經帶你參觀過了吧?
He did.  ls the Dodgers still... still losing?
是的. 道奇還是...  在輸?
I might be able to answer that question  if Carter over here
如果卡特能在這裏讓他閉上他的大嘴巴
stop running his nasty mouth.
或者我能回答你的那個問題
Cut the shit  and let's get to work.
別扯淡了，我們去幹活兒吧.
"Ain't That a Kick in the Head"]
- Ready.  - Lord, help us.
- 準備.  - 上帝保佑我們吧.
Don't be nervous, man.  Just go on and get to it.
不要緊張. 放輕鬆點，去吧.
You hear nothing,  you see nothing.
要做到充耳不聞, 視而不見
You only serve.
只要專心做好你的事.
Send federal troops to Little Rock?
要派聯邦軍隊去小巖城?
If it comes to it, yes.
如果真要是到了那一步，那麼是的.
I can't see any situation where  I'd send federal troops to the South.
我看不到有任何能讓我派聯邦軍隊去南部的理由
Ever. Could cause another Civil War.
從沒有.而且那會引發另一場內戰.
Sir, if the federal government  doesn't enforce Brown, then who will?
先生, 如果聯邦政府都無法實施布朗案的裁決  那麼還有誰可以呢?
The South must comply with the law.
南部一定要遵守聯邦法律.
It's just gonna take some time  to adjust, that's all.
他們只是需要一點時間去適應而已
I understand, Mr. President,
我明白, 總統先生
but if Faubus continues to block the  Negro children, then what do we do?
但是如果福伯斯繼續隔離黑鬼小孩  那我們要怎麼辦?
We must enforce  the Constitution.
我們必須要執行憲法的規定.
Give Faubus more time.
再多給福伯斯一點時間吧.
With a little persuading,  he'll back down.
還有，再勸勸他  相信他會作出讓步的
We just want to move slowly.
我們只是不想太急功近利.
- How'd it go?  - I almost shit myself.
- 怎麼樣?  - 我都快尿褲子了.
I dated a girl once. Every time  I hit her, she shit herself.
我以前約會過一個女孩  每次我揍她的時候她都會尿自己一身
- What?  - Got no sense.
- 什麼?  - 不要臉
- Shut up.  - You shut up.
- 閉嘴.  - 你閉嘴吧.
I put a towel down.
我放了一個毛巾在下面呢
You know, Marcella said  the very same thing last night
你知道，我昨晚送馬塞拉睡覺前
just before I put her to sleep.
她也說到了相同的事情
- Wow. You put her...  - Just like I did Ed.
- 哇噢，你送她...  - 就像我對待埃迪一樣.
I'd do it real quick.
我做得非常快.
' See you!  - Why?
- 你瞧你!  - 為什麼?
Dang...  Got the popcorn all over the sofa.
討厭... 沙發上到處都是爆米花
Your dad's gonna kill...
你爸爸會殺了...
Hey,Dad.
嗨，爸爸.
- Hi, Mr. Gaines.  - Hey, Dad.
- 嗨，蓋恩斯先生.  - 嗨，爸爸
Hey, Elroy.
嗨，埃爾羅伊.
Louis, I told you about letting these  kids watch that show.
路易斯, 我跟你說過  要讓那兩個孩子們看其他的電視節目
It's too scary.  They're too young for it.
這個電影太恐怖了.  他們的年紀不適合看這個
Turn it off.
關掉吧.
All you got to do is smile pretty,
你需要做的就是要笑得甜美一點
and a man will forget  everything he ever learned.
讓會讓男人就會忘記一切
Where your mama at?
你媽媽在哪兒?
Miss Gloria tried staying up,  but she went to sleep.
格羅瑞亞小姐想要熬夜來著，但是她睡著了.
Elroy, ain't nobody  asked you nothing.
埃爾羅伊, 沒人問你話.
Take your butt home before  your mama come up in here
在你媽媽來這裏收拾我們大家之前
and whup the both of us.
你快點轱轆回家吧
- Come on, Dad.  - Go on.
- 得了，爸爸.  - 快走吧.
- Bye.  - Turn it off.
- 拜.  - 把電視關掉.
Don't go stomping up the stairs,  wake your mama up.
上樓梯的時候輕一點  別吵醒你媽媽
What is that?
那是什麼?
Is that that Mamie Till stuff?
那是瑪米 提爾的照片?
- I want to go to this.  - Absolutely not.
- 我想要參與這事兒.  - 絕對不行.
How come?
為什麼?
Ain't no good can come of that.
那事兒不會帶給你任何好處的
Dad, you heard what Mama said?
爸爸，你聽到媽媽是怎麼說的?
That mess right there  happened down South.
那些破事兒是發生在南部
- This could have been me.  - It happened down South.
- 但那個人也有可能就是我.  - 那是南部的事.
I got out of there so we  could have us a better life.
正因為我離開了那裏  所以我們才能今天更好的生活
Right now, I'm working for the white  man, make things better for us.
眼下我在為白人工作  我只是為了讓事情對我們更有利.
And not just any white man, either.
而且也不是所有的白人都那樣
Put the lights off. Go to bed.
把燈關掉. 上床睡覺.
I have your chicken soup,  Mr. President.
我給你燉了點雞湯,總統先生
Just set it on the table, Cecil.
先放在桌子上吧, 塞西爾
Yes, sir.
好的，先生.
Did you ever complete school, Cecil?
你有沒有把學上完, 塞西爾?
I didn't go to school,  Mr. President.
我沒有上過學,總統先生.
I grew up on a cotton farm.
我是在棉花農場裏長大的.
I grew up on a farm.
我也是在農場裏長大的.
Do you have any children?
你有孩子嗎?
Yes, sir, I have two sons.
是的，先生，我有兩個兒子.
Do they go  to an all-colored school?
他們是在綜合學校上學的嗎?  （非種族隔離學校）
Yes, sir, they do.
是的，先生.
What is it?
怎麼了?
State Guard just blocked  all the colored kids again.
地方警衛隊又把有色人種的孩子們擋在外邊.
Faubus promised me the guards  would escort the kids in.
福伯斯跟我保證過那些警衛會護送孩子們進去
Governor of Arkansas lied,  Mr. President.
可見阿肯色州的州長在撒謊  總統先生.
What is wrong with him?  Why is he forcing me to do this?
他究竟有什麼毛病?  為什麼他非得逼我這麼做?
Yes, sir.
是的，先生.
Our next move  needs to be bold and swift.
我們的下一步行動必須要大膽而且迅速
I have today  issued an executive order
今天我將簽發一項總統命令
directing the use of troops  under federal authority
我們要發揮聯邦軍隊的效用
to aid in the execution  of federal law
以確保聯邦法令能在...
at Little Rock, Arkansas.
阿肯色州小巖城順利施行.
This became necessary...
這是必須的..
When the president  sent those troops down to Little Rock,
總統派遣了軍隊前往小岩石城
it was the first time I ever seen a  white man stick his neck out for us.
那也是我第一次見到一位白人  為了我們黑人的權益而承擔風險
I told Louis that the president was  gonna make things better for us.
我告訴路易斯  總統正在為我們爭取更好的生活.
All graduations are long.  She was so nosy.
畢業典禮總是那麼漫長  她還嗶嗶個沒完沒了.
I'm gonna make  some potato salad.
我去做點兒土豆沙拉.
Now he could see that I knew  what I was talking about.
現在他可以看到我所指的究竟是什麼
That was wonderful.  I'm so proud of you.
那太美妙了  我真為你感到驕傲.
- Thanks, Mama.  - That hat looks stupid.
- 謝謝，媽媽.  - 那個帽子看起來好傻.
Your face looks stupid.
你的臉才看起來好傻呢.
- Proud of you, too.  - Dad, did you see...
- 我也為你感到驕傲.  - 爸爸，你有沒有看到...
Don't start something in there.
別再在這裏瞎嚷嚷了
Did you see one white kid  in my school?
你有沒有在我的學校裏看到任何白人孩子?
Why couldn't Louis see that  the president made things better for us?
為什麼路易斯就看不到總統為了我們所做的努力W?
- Thank you.  - Cookie?
- 謝謝.  - 要點餅幹嗎?
- Cookies.  - Thanks.
- 要點餅幹嗎  - 謝謝.
Thank you.
謝謝
Boy, I told you  we was gonna be late!
我跟你說了我們會遲到的!
You cannot miss this bus!
你可不能錯過這趟巴士!
- Oh, Lord have mercy.  - Wait, a sec. Wait, wait, wait.
- 噢，仁慈的上帝呀  - 等一下，稍等.....
- What?  - Got to say good-bye.
- 什麼了?  - 我們必須得先說再見.
Bus can wait.
巴士是可以等的.
Tennessee is  a long ways away, Pop.
田納西州離這裏很遠.
Fisk is a really  good school, Dad.
費斯克可是一所很棒的大學.
You can change your mind  and go to Howard.
你可以去霍華德大學.
I cannot believe you are still  talking about Howard University.
我簡直不敢相信，都這會兒了  你居然還在扯什麼霍華德大學
- He's going to Fisk.  - I know, I know. It's just...
- 他要去費斯克大學.  - 我知道，我知道，只是...
It's just so far away, that's all.
只是覺得離家太遠了而已.
- That's the point.  - What's the point?
- 那就是重點所在.  - 什麼重點?
Give me a cigarette, and don't  tell me you don't smoke.
給我支煙吧，而且可別跟我說你不抽煙.
- I don't have one.  - Come here.
- 我沒煙.  - 過來.
- You know you want to cry, punk.  - Not for you.
- 你很想哭，是吧，傻瓜.  - 我又不是為你哭.
Look under your mattress.  I left you something.
回家後看一下你的床墊下面有什麼.  我給你留了點東西
- I can't protect him down South.  - The South has changed, Cecil.
- 他在南方我就無法保護他了.  - 南方已經跟過去不一樣了，塞西爾.
I'm too young for Playboy.
我還不到看「花花公子」的年紀呢.
The South ain't what it  was when you was there.
那裏已經不再是你曾經待過的那個南部了.
Ma, Louis is leaving me  his filthy magazines.
媽媽，路易斯把他的色情雜誌留給了我
- Stop lying on your brother.  - Why you slapping him?
- 別跟你兄弟瞎說.  - 為什麼你要扇他呀?
He's the one with the magazines.
他才是拿著雜誌的那個人.
- I love you, Mama.  - I love you, son.
- 我愛你，媽媽  - 我也愛你，兒子.
- I love you, Louis.  - I love you.
- 我愛你，路易斯  - 我也愛你
- I made you ham sandwiches.  - Thanks, Mama.
- 我給你做了火腿三明治  - 謝謝媽媽
Come on, Dad.
好了，爸爸
OK.
好吧
You're the first.
你是第一個
I know.
我知道
I'm really proud of you.
我真的很為你驕傲
I got to go, Dad.
我得走了，爸爸
I got to go.
我必須得走了
If you need anything, you call me.
如果你有什麼需要，就打電話給我
- All right.  - All right?
- 好的.  - 好嗎?
Bye, Mama.
拜 媽媽.
Bye, Louis.
拜 路易斯
It's all right.
沒事的
Remind me again why  we're doing this, please.
請再提醒我一下為什麼我們要這麼做
Somebody? Tell me?  That look like a mugging to me,
有人能告訴我嗎  那玩意看上去就像是一個苦瓜臉
- that's what that looks like.  - This is the art of French baking.
- 看起來就是那樣  - 那是法國的烘培藝術.
Negro, please.  "Art of French baking."
得了吧，黑鬼.  別跟我扯什麼"法國的烘培藝術 "
This is absolutely nothing.  That's what this is.
這很明顯狗屁都不是.
- I don't...  - Boy's always so simple.
- 我不...  - 男孩子的頭腦總是那麼簡單.
You want me to play with it?  I'll play with it.
你想讓我玩給你看嗎?  我來玩給你看吧
Play With it like this.
就像這樣.
It'd be good if it had a little...  a little nipple on it.
這會很好看，如果再給它弄個小...  弄個小乳頭在上面.
Come on, man.
得了，哥們.
That's how you play. You jiggle it.  You shake it, you know.
你不就是這麼玩的嗎.  你搖晃它. 你擺弄它.....
This fool.
這個傻子.
Good evening,  Mr. Vice President.
晚上好, 副總統先生
That looks like a tasty treat.
那看上去很美味呀
Yes, sir.
是的，先生
I brought you all something.
我給你們大家帶了點東西來.
Thank you, Mr. Vice President.
謝謝你，副總統先生.
I don't want to say anything negative
我不想說任何不利於那個...
about that Kennedy boy.  I'm sure he's a real nice fellow.
肯尼迪男孩的事兒.  我很肯定他是個很友善的傢伙
But do you really want that  spoiled rich son-of-a-bitch fuck
但是，你們真的想讓那個被寵壞的...
to be your next president?
富人家的婊子養的傢伙...  成為你們的下一任總統嗎?
Think about it.
好好想想吧.
We'll cheer for you,  Mr. Vice President.
我們會為你加油的，副總統先生
Thank you, Cecil.
謝謝你，塞西爾.
Let me ask you something,  in all candor,
讓我來問你點兒事兒吧  坦率的說,
as members of the Negro community,  what are your biggest concerns?
作為黑人社區的成員  你最關心的事情是什麼?
Now, come on now, boys.
說說看，小伙子們
Don't be shy.
別不好意思.
Holloway, come on.
霍洛維，你說說
- Well, since you asked, sir...  - I did.
- 好吧，因為你問到了，先生...  - 對，我在問你
The colored help gets paid almost  4O percent less than the white help.
同樣的活兒，支付給有色員工的薪水  比支付給白人的薪水要低40%
- Is that right?  - Yes, sir.
- 是這樣嗎?  - 是的，先生.
And it's very difficult for  the colored staff to be promoted.
而且有色員工基本沒有陞遷的機會.
I'll tell you what. When I'm president,  I'm gonna look into getting you boys
我告訴你吧，如果我是總統  我會為你們加薪
the raises and  the promotions you deserve.
並且讓你們都得到升職.
That... that would be swell, sir.
那.. 那會很棒，先生.
- You got my word on that.  - Thank you, sir.
- 我向你保證.  - 謝謝你，先生
Now, you tell your people  to vote for me,
那麼現在，你要讓你們的人為我投票
and that's exactly  what's gonna happen.
然後我說的那一切將會實現
Give that to somebody.
把那個分給大家.
What do you mean, you don't  want to date nobody?
你說的是什麼意思，你不想跟任何人約會?
After all these guys  that come after you?
尤其是有那麼多人在追你.....
- Girl, please. I'm just...  - Like that one?
- 我只是...  - 比如那一位?
I'm talking about you and Isaac.
我們現在說的是你和艾薩克.
Now, come on,  tell me what happened.
快點啦，告訴我發生什麼事了.
Y'all seemed happy.
你們倆看起來很開心.
See, I can't even have a normal  conversation with you, because...
你看吧，我都沒法跟你正常說話，因為...
- Hey.  - You looking for love, boy?
- 喂.  - 你在尋找真愛的嗎, 帥哥?
That's what we call the Lawson workshop,  the love school.
那就是為什麼我要把  勞森研討會稱為愛之學校的原因
- Is that what you're looking for?  - That's why I came to Fisk.
- 那就是你正在尋找的嗎?  - 那就是我來費斯克大學的原因.
Me, too.
我也是
- I'm Carol Hammie.  - Louis Gaines.
- 我是卡羅爾 阿米耶.  - 羅伊斯 蓋恩斯
Come on. Follow me.
來吧，跟著我.
You a country boy, ain't you?
你是個鄉下男孩, 是嗎?
He's a doctor. What does your dad do?
他是一名醫生.  你爸爸是做什麼的?
He's in politics.
他在政治領域工作.
You were gonna need help  finding this place anyway.
要沒有人幫忙你是很難找到這個地方的
...nor can you sustain it  over a month.
...而且你也無法維持超過一個月.
- Really?  - This requires time, commitment,
- 真的嗎?  - 這需要時間, 還需要有承擔,
dedication, discipline and focus.
要有獻身精神, 嚴格的紀律以及專注的注意力
And we are measuring our  accomplishments in waves, right?
而且我們得衡量我們取得的每一個階段性的成就，對嗎?
This is not a fly-by-night affair.  This doesn't happen over a week.
這不是一個能夠投機取巧的事情  過去一周都沒有再發生過那樣的事了
This requires a fierce discipline,  which is what we've been discussing.
這需要一個我們一直以來  所探討的嚴格的紀律
How do you measure these things?
我們如何來衡量這些事情呢?
We go back, and we look  at somebody like Gandhi.
我們要回頭去看看像甘地那樣的人
Together, we are gonna study  and examine Gandhi's techniques.
我們要一起去學習甘地的經驗和技巧
What has been so effective  in South Africa, so effective in India,
為什麼他在南非和印度的影響力會那麼大
for his own people and others,
無論是對於他自己的人民，還是對於其他國家的人民
and we're gonna employ it  right here, in Nashville.
我們要借鑒他們的經驗，而且要用在納什維爾.
So we're gonna form an army.  You and I.
我們要組建一支部隊.你們和我
This army has one weapon.  That weapon is love.
這支部隊只有一種武器  那個武器就是愛
Now, I am of the... yes.
此刻，我就是... 你說.
If our only weapon is love,
如果我們唯一的武器是愛
and then their weapons  are weapons,
而他們的武器是真的武器,
- I mean, isn't that dangerous?  - Oh, you can be killed.
- 我是說，那不是很危險嗎?  - 噢，你會被他們殺掉的.
If anybody's uncomfortable with that,  you know where the door is.
如果有誰不喜歡我們的主張,  你知道門在哪兒.
I understand that sounds  provocative, but it's true.
我明白那聽起來充滿了挑釁，但那是事實
All right, kids.  It's show time.
好了，同學們  現在是演出時間
"Function at the Junction"]
Gandhi has demonstrated for us  that the brown man,
甘地已經向我們證明了  在他們國家或者任何地方
in his native land, or anywhere  that he's being oppressed...
生活著的那些棕色人種...
...can pull himself out of segregation
...可以不再忍受脫離種族隔離制度的壓迫
with patience, with persistence,
只要有無比的耐心、堅持和毅力,
with intelligence and thought,  with discipline...
運用自己智慧和思想，以及自律...
...and a bit  of a sense of humor.
...還有一點點幽默感.  我們就可以做到
You know y'all can't sit here.
你們知道你們是不可以坐在這裏的
We would like to be served, please.
我們很願意接受你的服務
This is unprecedented,  what we're talking about,
我們所談論的事情並不是沒有先例
but it needs a patience  that none of us have ever seen.
但是這需要我們有足夠的耐心.
You can order food  in the colored section,
你可以去有色人種的那個區域點餐
but I'm not gonna be  serving you here.
但是在這裏  我不會為你提供服務的
We are organized.  We have a leader with every group.
我們是有組織的.  我們每一個團隊都設有一名領導.
We have lookouts  with pocket change
我們有負責觀察和監督的人員
and the local phone numbers  for ambulances ready,
以及當地的救護車電話號碼
and when one wave comes  off that lunch counter, what follows?
一旦有人在那個餐館裏遇到麻煩  接下來要做什麼?
A whole 'nother wave of Negro students
其他坐在餐館裏的黑人學生
sitting at that lunch counter,  blowing their mind.
就要上前向他們陳述你們的想法
We would like  to be served, please.
請為我們提供服務，謝謝
Now, who wants to role-play?
現在，有誰願意參與角色扮演?
Jim, I need your help over here.
吉姆，我這裏需要幫助
Now, y'all know you're  not supposed to sit there.
你們都知道你們不應該坐在那裏
- Attack.  - Get up, nigger! Get up!
- 攻擊.  - 站起來，黑鬼，站起來!
This is an experiment.
這只是一次試驗.
So do whatever it takes  to break their spirits.
所以，要盡一切可能去挫敗對方的銳氣
- Come on, get up, nigger.  - Use the language.
- 快點，站起來，黑鬼  - 要使用語言.
I need to hear "nigger" coming  out of your mouth.
我需要聽到從你們的嘴裏說出 "黑鬼" 這個詞
- I need to hear "coon."  - I don't feel comfortable saying that.
- 我需要聽到你們說 "coon. "(也是侮辱黑人的稱謂)  - 說那個會讓我感到不舒服.
You came here to get yourself prepared  and to get her prepared.
既然你來到這裏，就要做好準備  也要讓她做好準備
So let me hear it now.
那麼，現在說給我聽吧
- Nigger.  - Louder.
- 黑鬼.  - 大聲點.
Say the words like you mean it.
你要讓別人聽起來好像你是認真的
- Nigger.  - Louder.
- 黑鬼.  - 大聲點
You are a nigger!
你是個黑鬼!
You need to be sitting  in the colored seating.
你得去坐在有色人種的座位上
This is not for you,  you cannot be served here.
這裏不是你待的地方  在這裏你不會得到服務的
You need to do as you're told  and sit in your place.
你應該按照這位女士的吩咐  去坐在你該坐的地方
- You are a nigger.  - Make her believe it.
- 你是個黑鬼  - 要讓她相信你
- I don't believe you.  - You're a nigger.
- 我不相信你  - 你是個黑鬼
You know that's where  the colored people sit.
你知道有色人種應該坐在哪裏
You see these people over here?  They're in their section over here.
看到那邊的那些人類嗎  他們就坐在他們自己的區域裏
You coon ass!  Get up, you nigger!
你個死黑鬼!  快起來，你個黑鬼!
If you want us to shop  in this establishment, make them go.
如果你想讓我們在這裏買東西  那就別讓他們待在這裏
Come on, Robert, let's go.
快點，羅伯特，我們走吧
Nigger lover, get out!
你們這對黑鬼鴛鴦, 快點出去!
- Get up, monkey. Get up!  - What is this?
- 快起來，死猴子，起來!  - 怎麼回事?
Are you listening to us?
你沒聽到我們的話嗎?
This says "whites only."
這裏寫著"只歡迎白人. "
Get up, nigger. Get up!
起來，黑鬼, 起來!
- Coons here?  - What are you doing here?
- 有黑鬼在這裏呀?  - 你們在這裏做什麼呢?
- Does it say "coons?"  - "Whites only."
- 難道這裏有寫著 "黑鬼?"  - "只歡迎白人. "
You don't belong here with them.  This? What is this, huh?
你不屬於這裏. 這是什麼?
- Does it say "coons" here, huh?  - What are you doing here?
- D難道這裏有寫著 "黑鬼?"  啊?  - 你們在這裏做什麼?
- Pay attention.  - No, this is whites only.
- 仔細聽著.  - 不，只有白人能待在這裏.
You don't belong here at all.
你們不屬於這裏.
What are you reading?  I didn't know niggers could read.
你在讀什麼呢?  我還不知道黑鬼也會閱讀
What are you, stupid?  You're a nigger lover now?
你是什麼玩意兒, 傻X  你們現在是一對黑鬼鴛鴦了嗎?
Get up, you nigger!  Look at me!
快起來，你個死黑鬼  看著我!
- Look at me!  - What are you doing?
- 看著我!  - 你們在這裏做什麼??
You disrespectful monkey. Huh?
你個沒教養的死猴子?
Do you understand?  You understand?
你聽明白了嗎? 明白了嗎?
Stop it! Stop it!
住手，住手!
What do you think you're doing here?
你以為你們能在這裏幹嘛呢?
Get up! Get up, you nigger!  Look at me! Look at me!
起來，快起來，你個死黑鬼  看著我，看著我!
That up there or is that here?
在那上邊，還是在這裏?
You don't have to tell me,
你用不著告訴我,
- but you have to decide.  - I was a nigger.
- 但是你必須得做個決定.  - 我是個黑鬼.
- Go back to where you came from!  - Here, you want some coffee?
- 滾回你來的地方!  - 給你，你不是想來點咖啡嗎?
...the niggers are better  off in their own schools
...黑鬼們最好滾回他們自己的學校
than they are in the white schools.
而不是待在白人的學校裏.
- To serving our country.  - Serving our country.
- 為我們的國家服務.  - 為我們的國家服務.
My man.
我的兄弟.
I feel rich right now.  I like the way that tastes.
我現在覺得很富有  我喜歡這個口味.
They got no business out here.
這裏沒他們什麼事
...better off in their  own schools than they are
...最好滾回他們自己的學校
in the white schools.
而不是待在白人的學校裏.
You're all sentenced to 3O days
你們幾個都被判定....
- in the countyjail.  - What?
- 在郡監獄服刑30天.  - 什麼?
Bailiff, get these  niggers out of here.
法警, 把這些黑鬼帶離這裏
Something special  is going on down here, Dad.
這裏發生了一些很特別的事情，爸爸
What's so special about  another colored man in jail?
對於一個進了監獄的有色人種可言  還能有什麼特別的事?
What you doing  with my hard earned money, Pop?
你究竟在拿老子辛辛苦苦賺來的錢  搞蝦米灰機?
Are you even in school?
你還在學校嗎?
I'm trying to change  the way Negroes...
我是在試著改變黑鬼的...
You're breaking the law.
你違法了法律.
That judge just sentenced you  to 3O days in the county workhouse.
那個法官剛剛才宣判你去郡教養所服刑30天.
You fixing to get killed.
在那裏你會死的
If I can't sit at any  lunch counter I want,
如果我都無法坐在任何我想坐的餐館裏,
then I might as well be dead.
那麼我還不如死了算了.
- We're fighting for our rights.  - Rights?
- 我們在為我們的權利而奮鬥.  - 權利?
- What are you talking about?  - We're trying to change
- 你究竟是說什麼呢?  - 我們在試著改變
the nation's consciousness  toward the American Negro.
這個國家的民眾對待黑鬼的態度和意識.
Them postcards you've been sending me?
那你寄給我的那些明信片是怎麼回事?
- You're a damn liar.  - I have been in school.
- 你就是該死的謊話精.  - 我一直在學校.
Who do you think you're talking to?
你以為你是在跟誰說話呢?
I brought you into this world,  I can take you out of it.
是我把你帶到了這個世界上  我也一樣可以帶你離開那裏
- Y'all been able to talk to him?  - Talk to who?
- 你們一直跟他有聯絡?  - 誰?
- Louis.  - Yeah, we talk to him.
- 路易斯  - 對
Said he's joined something  called the "Freedom Riders,"
他說他參加了一個什麼東東  叫什麼「自由騎士」
whatever the hell  that's supposed to mean.
搞不明白那究竟是個什麼意思
You gonna see him?
你要去看他嗎?
I been fixing to trying to see him.
我一直想要去看他
Every time I do,  Cecil get all riled up.
但是每次我一提這茬兒  塞西爾就跟我發火
So I don't know when  that's gonna happen.
所以我也不曉得我究竟什麼時候才能去看他
"Fixing to trying."  See, that's the problem.
"試著想要.... "  你看，這就是問題所在
You got to stop trying,  and you just got to do it.
想去就去，別老是想來想去的
He take you  to the White House yet?
他有沒有帶你去過白宮?
No. Cecil say we're going soon.
沒有，塞西爾說我們很快就會去了
"Cecil say, Cecil say."
"塞西爾說，塞西爾說. "
Four years. That's what makes  you a little bit gullible, darling.
都四年了.你還是那麼容易就相信他說的話，親愛的
I don't understand.  I don't understand why he can't
我不明白.  我也不明白為什麼他就不能....
- get the president to do something.  - See, Gina, that's your problem.
- ...讓總統幹點啥.  - 你看，吉娜，這就是你的問題所在.
You just say stupid stuff.
你就知道說這些傻乎乎的屁話
President got more to do than be  thinking about Louis' foolishness.
總統有那麼多的事要做  那裏有功夫去理會路易斯的那點愚蠢的破事
You know,  why don't you just shut up?
為什麼你就不能乾脆閉上嘴?
It's just a mess.  Be nice.
現在遇上這麼糟心的事兒  你就不能表現得友好一點嗎.
Who told you  you could tell me to shut up?
誰跟你說了你可以讓我閉嘴的?
- Well...  You...  - Go get me a drink.
- 嗯... 你..  - 去給我拿點喝的來.
I want some scotch.
我要喝點兒蘇格蘭威士忌
Well, I personally think Louis is  gonna get every one of us killed.
我個人的想法是路易斯會  把我們大家都害死的
They coming to get us.  They coming to get us.
他們會來抓我們的.  他們會來抓我們的.
He crazy like his mama.
他就跟他媽媽一樣瘋狂
I meant it in a good way.
我是說，在好的方面.
I'm sorry!  I'm sorry.
對不起! 對不起
Get back over here.
回來這裏啦.
Let me get your ass.
我還是跟這你們進去吧
I received also a wire from  President Eisenhower, which says...
我收到了艾森豪威爾總統的一個電報  上面說...
The president lives  at the White House
總統會住在白宮
until the moment the next one  is sworn in.
一直到下一位總統宣誓就職
So the staff has exactly two hours
所以，在總統的就職典禮進行期間
during the inauguration ceremony,  to move the old president out
員工只有兩個小時的時間  要把上一任總統的東西搬出去
and move the new one in.
然後再把新任總統的東西搬進來.
They say  this new white boy's smooth.
他們說，這個新來的白人小子很圓滑
I just need to get my  butt home to Gloria.
我只想快點回家找格羅瑞亞
'Cause these hours,  they're killing us.
忙活這半天累得快要死了
How's your boy doing, Cecil?
你兒子怎麼樣了, 塞西爾?
Gentlemen, the president's arriving.
先生們, 總統到了.
- OK.  - Where shall we start?
- 好的  - 我們要從哪兒開始?
I'm not sure.  This end, maybe over there?
我也不確定  也許我們從那邊開始?
- Thank you.  - Right this way, Mr. President.
- 謝謝  - 請這邊走，總統先生
- Hello, everyone.  - Mr. President.
- 大家好  - 總統先生
I am thrilled to be  working with all of you
能和你們大家一起共事讓我很激動
over the next four years.
在接下來的四年裏
Eight years, Jack.
是八年，傑克
Well, you see who wears  the pants around here.
好吧，你們會看到誰會在這裏當家
I'm not gonna remember any  of your names, but I'm gonna try.
我不一定能記住你們每一位的姓名  但是我會試試看的
Jessie. It's a good thing you're here  'cause I'm gonna forget.
傑西. 你在這裏會很好  因為我會忘記的
- Thank you. This is Lorraine.  - Pleasure to meet you.
- 謝謝你. 這位是羅琳.  - 很榮幸見到你.
- Mr. President.  - How are you, James?
- 總統先生  - 你好，詹姆斯先生?
- Carter.  - Pleasure, Mr. President.
- 卡特.  - 很榮幸見到你，總統先生.
- Carter.  - This is Cecil.
- 卡特.  - 這位是塞西爾.
- Pleasure to meet you, Mr. President.  - How are you?
- 很榮幸見到你，總統先生.  - 你好?
- William.  - Mrs. Kennedy.
- 威廉.  - 肯尼迪夫人.
- Greg.  - How are you?
- 格雷格.  - 你好?
Winslow.
溫斯洛.
I got it. She's all right.
我揀起來了，她沒事.
Pleasure to meet you,  Miss Caroline.
很高興見到你，卡羅琳小姐.
- Miles.  - Miles.
- 邁爾斯.  - 邁爾斯.
What's that on your breath,  Gloria? Stop, OK. Stop.
你的呼吸裏是什麼味道,  格羅瑞亞? 住手，好嗎，住手.
- What's that?  - Baby, that's gin.
- 那是什麼?  - 寶貝，那是杜松子酒的味道.
- I can smell it from here.  - It said "Addison's disease."
- 我從這裏都可以聞得出來  - 那叫作阿狄森氏病
Stop. Stop it, will you stop?
住手，住手啦，你能住手嘛?
Did you take Charlie  to the dentist today?
你今天有沒有帶查理去看牙醫?
Somebody at the White House  got Addison's disease?
在白宮有人得了阿狄森氏病?
No, I did not take Charlie  to the dentist today.
沒有，我今天沒有帶查理去看牙醫.
And what you asking me about it for?  You never home.
而且，你問那些做什麼?  你又從來不在家.
Now you gonna act like you gonna  take Charlie to the dentist?
你問這個就好像你會帶查理去看牙醫一樣
You ain't never here.  I don't know how you gonna take him.
你從來都不會在家.  我都不知道你要怎麼樣帶他們去
His teeth fall out,  waiting on you to take him.
他的牙齒脫落了  他等著你帶他去看牙醫呢.
Just go to bed, Gloria.  I'll take him tomorrow.
快睡覺吧，格羅瑞亞  我明天會帶他去
How many pairs of shoes  does she have?
她究竟有多少雙鞋子呀?
I said, how many pairs of shoes  does Mrs. Jackie Kennedy have?
我問你呢，傑奎琳·肯尼迪夫人究竟有多少雙鞋子呀?
How the hell do I know?
我他媽的怎麼知道?
You're in that 0l' White House  day and night.
你不是一天到晚都待在白宮裏嗎.
Thought you knew everything.
我還以為你無所不知呢.
Coming in,  trying to tell me what to do.
可你就會一進家門  告訴我我應該做什麼
Worried about me drinking.
擔心我是不是喝酒了.
You ought to be worried  about your house.
塞西爾，你應該多操心自己家裏的事
Our boy's in jail, Cecil.
我們的兒子還在監獄裏呢.
Our boy's in jail,  and you can't come home.
我們的兒子在監獄裏  可你都不能回家
You... You don't see I'm here,  trying to talk to you?
你... 你沒看到我正在試著跟你談話嗎?
I bet you wish I spoke French,  just like Jackie.
我敢打賭你肯定希望我能說法語  就像傑奎琳一樣.
Jackie Kennedy.
傑奎琳 肯尼迪
Que sera, sera.
該怎樣, 就怎樣.（法語）
You like that?
你喜歡這樣?
You like the way she talk?
你喜歡她說話的方式嗎?
Cecil,  you hear me talking to you.
塞西爾，你聽沒聽到我在跟你說話呢
You ain't asleep.
你根本就沒睡著.
Bobby told the president
鮑比告訴總統說
they shouldn't be worried about  the Negro sit-ins.
他們不應該擔心那些黑鬼靜坐示威的事
Polls show the US  does not support civil rights.
民意調查顯示美國的民權問題始終沒有得到改善.
Told you that white boy was smooth.  A little too smooth for my money.
我跟你說過那個白人男孩（總統）很圓滑  依我看來他有點太狡猾了
- Hey, Cecil, how's your boy doing?  - Out of jail, says he's back in school,
- 喂，塞西爾，你兒子怎麼樣了?  - 已經出獄了，他說他已經回去學校了,
but I think he's doing  that freedom riding thing.
但我覺得他還在從事  他那個什麼自由騎士的事兒
How's Gloria doing  with that drinking?
格羅瑞亞還在喝酒嗎?
She's hanging-
還在斷斷續續地喝.
They say that cat  that's playing is a big deal.
他們說那個傢伙的演奏非常棒
- Pablo Casals, world famous.  - Course he's world famous.
- 帕布羅·卡薩爾斯，在全世界都很有名  - 他當然很有名啦.
You think Mrs. Kennedy  is gonna have, uh...
你覺得肯尼迪夫人會，嗯 ...
some backwoods country fiddle  band playing out there for her?
讓什麼不知名的小人物來這裏為她演奏小提琴?
- Man.  - Why don't you start a band?
- 得啦.  - 為什麼你不整一個樂隊?
Maybe you can go out there, too.
也許你也可以出去那裏演奏呢
You know what, in fact,  let's all start a band.
你知道嗎，事實上  我們可以一起組建一個樂隊
I'll play the bongos.  What about you?
我會彈奏小手鼓.  你準備彈奏什麼?
I play a mean... skin flute.
我會吹奏長笛  （skin flute也有口交的意思）.
- ♪ Babalu.  - Casals is a righteous soul.
- # 巴巴魯.  - 卡薩爾斯是一個正直的人.
He refuses to play in any country  that recognizes Franco's regime.
他拒絕去任何一個承認佛朗哥政權的國家演奏  （弗朗西斯科佛朗哥是西班牙的獨裁領袖）
Who's Franco?
佛朗哥是誰?
- Forget it, man.  - Huh?
- 當我沒說.  - 嗯?
Forget it. You're ignorant.
當我沒說，你太無知了.
Carol, are you tired?
卡蘿爾, 你累了嗎?
You just want me to put my head  on your shoulder.
你是不是想讓我靠在你肩膀上
What wrong with that?
那有什麼不對嗎?
I'm not putting my head  on your shoulder.
我才不會靠在你的肩膀上啦.
You can.
你當然可以的
Ever been  on a freedom bus before?
以前從沒坐過自由巴士?
- No, it's my first time.  - No?
- 沒有，這是我第一次乘坐.  - 沒有嗎?
- How's your boyfriend feel about that?  - My boyfriend?
- 你男朋友對此有何看法?  - 我男朋友?
Yeah. I mean,  this must upset him, right?
嗯，我是說  這會惹他不開心吧，對嗎?
You being on this bus down here.
你現在坐在這輛巴士上.
- I don't have a boyfriend.  - You don't have a boyfriend?
- 我沒有男朋友  - 你沒男朋友?
How do you not have a boyfriend?
你怎麼可能沒有男朋友?
- You want some peanuts?  - No, thank you.
- 要不要吃點花生?  - 不要了，謝謝
- You like peanuts or...?  - I don't like peanuts.
- 你喜歡吃花生還是...?  - 我不喜歡花生.
- I'm too hot to eat.  - Hey, can I have some of those?
- 我不能吃東西.  - 喂，我可以吃點兒嗎?
- Long bus ride.  - OK.
- 這是一次長途旅行.  - 好的.
Louis, what is that?
路易斯，那是什麼?
- It's a cross. It's a cross.  - Driver, turn! Turn the bus!
- 那是一個十字架. 那是一個十字架.  - 司機，轉彎，快轉彎
Oh, shit.
噢，靠.
Niggers, get out here!
黑鬼們，滾出來!
Nigger, go home! Nigger, go home!
黑鬼，滾回家吧, 黑鬼，滾回家吧!
Oh, my God.  Everybody out!
噢，上帝呀. 大家都出去
"In an old house in Paris
在巴黎的一所外面蓋滿了...
that was covered with vines...
葡萄藤的老房子裏...
...lived 12 little girls  in two straight lines.
...住著12位小女孩
The smallest one  was Madeline."
其中最小的那一位叫瑪德琳
- Like Caroline.  - Mm-hm.
- 就像卡羅琳嗎.  - 嗯
"She was not afraid of mice."
她一點都不害怕老鼠
Why do people ride  in the freedom bus?
為什麼人們要乘坐那輛自由巴士呢?
Uncle Bobby told my daddy
鮑比叔叔告訴我爸爸說
that the freedom bus  exploded today.
今天有一輛自由巴士爆炸了
I can't tell you  if I walked off the bus
我不能告訴你我是如何離開那輛巴士的
or if I crawled off  or if someone pulled me off.
是我自己從車裏爬出來的  還是有人拉我出來的
I didn't know if my boy  was dead or alive.
我不知道我兒子是否還活著
When I got off the bus,  a man came up to me,
當我從那輛車裏出來的時候  一個男人向我走了過來
and I'm coughing and strangling,
當時我正在劇烈咳嗽，幾乎要窒息而死了
and he said, "Boy, you all right?"
然後我聽到他說, "孩子，你沒事嗎?"
And I nodded my head,  and the next thing I knew,
我點了點頭  我所知道的下一件事就是
I was on the ground.
我躺在地上
He had hit me with a baseball bat.
他在用一個棒球棒用力地打我.
Hello.
你好.
Hi, Dad.  I'm in Mississippi.
嗨，爸爸.  我現在在密西西比.
I thought you was in Alabama.
我還以為你在阿拉巴馬.
We spent two weeks in jail  there, now we're in Mississippi.
我們在那裏的監獄裏待了兩周  現在我們在密西西比.
I want you to listen  to me, Louis.
我希望你能聽我說，路易斯.
I want you to come home.
我希望你能回家
I know we ain't seen eye to eye,
我知道我們對一些事情的看法有分歧
but your mama,  she wants you home.
但是你媽媽她，  她很想你能回家
- They're keeping me.  - How long?
- 他們扣留了我.  - 要多久?
- Where is he?  - I don't know.
- 他在哪兒?  - 我不知道.
They said three months.
他們說大概要三個月.
When I get out,  I'm gonna take another ride.
等我出去的時候  我會開始另一次自由之旅.
- What are you talking about?  - What's he saying?
- 你在說什麼呀?  - 他怎麼說?
Let me talk to him.  Give me that phone.
讓我跟他說，把電話給我.
It is my right to ride that bus.  That is my legal right.
搭乘那輛巴士，那是我的權利  那是我的合法權利
I will exercise my rights  as an American citizen.
作為一名美國公民，我要運用我的權利
American citizen.  What you talking about?
美國公民.  你說什麼吶?
You know what  they're gonna do to you?
你知道他們會如何對待你嗎?
They're gonna lynch you
他們會將你處以私刑
and then they're gonna throw  your little ass in the river.
他們會把你扔進河裏
They're gonna kill you.
他們會殺了你
Ma, then they're just  gonna have to kill me.
媽媽，那麼他們起碼得殺了我，才能阻止我
...Negro  and white in Birmingham
...伯明翰的黑鬼和白人
have been building up  to scenes with clashes, like this.
一直在製造類似的此種衝突.
The situation was perilously  close to an explosion.
現在的情形非常嚴峻，幾乎要引發一次暴動了
Arrests were made in mass lots.
警方已經拘捕了大量的肇事人員.
Everyone charged  with the same offense...
並且所有都因為相同的原因遭到了起訴...
Here you are, Mr. President.
給你，總統先生.
I'll wait for your signature.
我會等你簽完字.
City police were  carrying out their pledge
城市警察已經在著手擴大監獄的容量
to fill their jails to  capacity if necessary.
以備不時之需
They are acting  according to the wishes...
他們這樣做的目的是為了迎合...的意願...
I don't know what country  I'm looking at.
我都不知道我現在看到的  這個究竟是什麼國家
...tone of the city for many years.
...這種論調已經持續了許多年
Get off! Get off!
出去，出去!
Residents here  have taken to the streets
在阿拉巴馬州伯明翰市,
in Birmingham, Alabama,  to bring attention to their efforts
住在這裏的人們走上街頭  去關注他們為了對抗美國政府
against the segregation  of black Americans.
對於美國黑人所實施的種族隔離制度所作出的努力
This is following earlier boycotts  in Birmingham to pressure...
這是早些時候發生在伯明翰的  為了向....施壓的抵抗示威活動...
Hey, Louis, man, that little  nigga might be onto something.
路易斯，那個小黑鬼可能做了點兒什麼事吧
Stop calling him a nigga,  'cause he ain't no nigga.
不許再叫他黑鬼,  因為他不是黑鬼.
What's wrong, baby?
有什麼問題嘛，寶貝?
- What's wrong with me is this.  - What are you talking about?
- 就是這個問題.  - 你說什麼呢?
This is what's wrong with me.  This is wrong. This is wrong.
那就是問題所在  那是不對的，那是不對的.
- We ain't been wrong yet.  - I can't do this to Cecil.
- 我們也沒有做錯什麼.  - 我不能這麼對待塞西爾.
We ain't doing it to Cecil.  I'm doing it to you.
我們怎麼做又不是衝著塞西爾  我這麼做是為了你
I want you out of my house.
我希望你能離開我的房子.
Why do you think God brought us  next to each other each day?
那你覺得為什麼上帝  會讓我們倆每天都待在一起
- God ain't got nothing to do with this.  - He put you right next door to me.
- 這跟上帝一點兒關係都沒有.  - 是他讓你住在了我的隔壁.
You always talking about how  lonely you are without Cecil
你不是總在說塞西爾待在白宮的時候  你有多麼多麼孤獨和寂寞...
being at the White House,  and you need a man that can
而且你需要一個男人能像我一樣..
appreciate the love and the  woman that you are, like I do.
欣賞你，並且感激你所付出的愛...
I want your number-running  ass up out of my house,
我希望你這快點把你的賭棍屁股挪出我家門
off of my sofa right now.
馬上從我的沙發上起來.
I'm... I'm through.  I told you.
我... 我們倆結束了.  我已經告訴你了.
Let me make  a demonstration for you.
讓我來證明給你看.
Don't come here with  this bullshit crazy talk.
別再來這裏發表你的那些狗屁演說
- It's not.  - Some more of this...
- 不是那個了.  - 比那個更扯...
This is you, right? You got  your direction that you move in.
這個是你, 對嗎?  你正在朝著你的方向前進.
- What you doing with my hangers?  - This is you, and this is me.
- 你拿我的衣架瞎搞什麼呢?  - 這一個是你, 這一個是我.
Now, we seem like we don't fit at all.  We just crash into each other.
現在，我們看上去好像完全不合拍  我們只是不小心碰到了一起
But then when  you align things properly,
可是接下來 我們開始慢慢回到了正確的位置上
like God putting you  next door to me,
就像上帝安排你住在了我的隔壁一樣
everything kind of works out.
所有的事看起來都有了轉機.
And even if you slow down,  I got you.
即使你的熱情減退了，我也能明白你的心意
You need to get your yellow  ass up out of my house.
抬起你的髒屁股，滾出我的房子
- We need each other.  - What I need is my husband.
- 我們需要彼此  - 我需要的是我的丈夫.
And not to be laying up here  in the gutter with you.
而不是和你待在破貧民窟裏
On average, how many pills do  you think I take a day, Cecil?
就平均而言，你覺得我一天大概  要吃多少藥，塞西爾?
About... 103, sir.
差不多... 103, 先生.
- Help me up.  - Mr. President.
- 扶我起來.  - 總統先生.
I know your son is a Freedom Rider.
我知道你兒子是一名自由騎士.
He's in prison right now in Birmingham  with Martin Luther King.
此刻他正和馬丁.路德.金待在伯明翰的監獄裏
Do you, uh...
你...
...you know how he is, sir?
...你知道他怎麼樣嗎, 先生?
I'm guessing he's pretty beat up,  but based on his record,
我猜他應該被打得夠嗆  但是根據他的記錄來看
he must be used to it.
他肯定早已經習慣了
Cecil, he's been arrested 16 times  over the past two years.
塞西爾, 過去兩年裏他已經被逮捕過16次了.
Yes, sir.
是的，先生.
- Will that be all, sir?  - That's it.
- 沒事了嗎, 先生?  - 就這樣吧.
You know, I never understood
你知道，我以前一直都不明白
what you all really went through...
你們究竟都經歷過什麼...
...until I saw that.
...直到我看到了那個.
My brother says these kids have...
我兄弟說那些孩子們...
...changed his heart.
...改變了他的心意.
They've changed mine, too.
他們也改變了我的
The fires of discord are burning  in every city North and South,
失望和紛爭之火在  北部以及南部的每座城市燃燒
where legal remedies  are not at hand.
在南北方沒有法律補救措施的地方燃燒。
Redress is sought in the streets,
人們上街示威、遊行、抗議，
in demonstrations,  parades and protests.
以此來尋求補救之法....
I am therefore  asking the Congress
因此，我要求
to enact legislation
國會立法
giving all Americans the right  to be served in facilities
賦予所有美國人在賓館、
which are open to the public.
餐廳、劇場、...
Hotels, restaurants, theaters,
零售店以及類似公共場
retail stores  and similar establishments.
享受服務的權利。
This seems to me to be  an elementary right.
這在我看來是一項基本權利.
Its denial is  an arbitrary indignity
對這項基本權利的剝奪是恣意損害公民尊嚴的行為
that no American in 1963  should have to endure, but many do.
是1963年的美國人不應當被迫容忍的行為  但有許多人卻在容忍
A great change is at hand.
一場重大變革的變革即將到來，
And our task, our obligation,  is to make that revolution,
而我們的任務、我們的義務是使這場革命  這場變革對於所有人都是
that change,  peaceful and constructive for all.
和平的和具有建設性的
Those who do nothing are  inviting shame as well as violence...
無所作為者是在自取恥辱和鼓勵暴力...
Hey. Hey, Cecil.  Cecil, what's wrong?
喂，塞西爾  塞西爾，怎麼了?
Cecil?
塞西爾?
They blew his...
他們打中了他...
...head off.
...的頭.
- Who are you talking about?  - Kennedy.
- 你說的是誰呀?  - 肯尼迪.
President Kennedy was shot
肯尼迪總統被槍擊了
as he drove from Dallas airport  to downtown Dallas...
當他乘車從達拉斯機場前往達拉斯市中心時...
They killed him.
他們殺了他.
Governor Connally of Texas  in the car with him was also shot.
和他同乘一輛車的時任德州州長康納利  也同時遭到槍擊
It is reported that  three bullets rang out.
據報道稱，現場一共有三發子彈
A Secret Serviceman has been...
一位前海軍陸戰隊員...
They killed our man.
他們殺死了我們的老大.
"He's dead." Whether he  referred to President Kennedy or not
"他死了. " 他是否與肯尼迪總統有關聯
is not yet known.
目前還不得而知
The president, cradled in the  arms of his wife, Mrs. Kennedy,
總統倒在她的妻子肯尼迪夫人的懷中
was carried to an ambulance  and the car rushed
直到救護車前來將他們帶離現場
to Parkland Hospital outside Dallas...
前往達拉斯城外的帕克蘭紀念醫院...
Mrs. Kennedy refused  to change her clothes,
肯尼迪夫人拒絕更換她的服裝
so that everybody could see  what they did to her husband.
因此，所有的人都可以看到  他們對她的丈夫所做的事
The last time  I saw that much blood
我最後一次見到那麼多的血
was the day my daddy was killed.
是在我爸爸被殺害的那一天.
Please tell me how I could help you.
請告訴我要如何才能幫到你.
Ma, what you doing?
媽媽，你在幹嘛
Here. Want you to take this box  and put it in the basement.
給你，我想讓你把這個盒子帶到地下室去
- Make sure you label it "trophies."  - This is Louis' stuff, Ma.
- 要記得在上面貼上「獎盃」的標籤  - 這是路易斯的東西，媽媽
You know he gonna be pissed.
你知道你這麼做會惹惱他的
I don't care nothing about  Louis being pissed.
我才不在乎路易斯是不是會被惹惱.
I'm the one pissed.  He ain't been here in three years.
現在我才是被惹惱的那個人  三年來他從未回來過這裏
Why you pissed, Mama?
你生什麼氣呢，媽媽?
And don't put that next  to myjarred okra either.
也不要把那個東西放在我的秋葵罐子邊上
Ain't nobody trying to smell  that stankin' okra.
才沒有人樂意聞那個臭得要命的秋葵呢
And when you come back, I want  you to get me some fish food.
你回來的時候，幫我帶一點新鮮的食物
Look what the president...
看看總統...
...Mrs. Kennedy gave me.
...這是肯尼迪夫人送給我的.
Belonged to the president.
這是屬於肯尼迪總統的.
Gloria...
格羅瑞亞...
President was killed.
總統被殺害了.
I'm really sorry about the president.
關於總統的事，我很遺憾
I really am.
我真的很遺憾.
But you and that White House  can kiss my ass.
但是你和那個白宮跟我一毛錢關係都沒有
I don't care what  goes on in that house.
我才不在乎那所房子裏發生的事.
I care about what goes on in this house.
我在乎的是這所房子裏發生的事
"I'll Close My Eyes"]
I knew that Gloria had been  unhappy for some time now.
我知道格羅瑞亞最近一段時間  一直都很不開心
I knew that's probably  why she drank.
我知道那也許就是她喝酒的原因
She wanted me to get along  better with Louis.
她希望我跟路易斯能相處得更好一點
I didn't know how.
可是我不知道應該怎麼做
I couldn't.
而且我也做不到
I could cut back them  long hours at the White House.
我可以減少待在白宮的時間.
And I did just that.
而且我也盡量在那麼做
How many pairs of shoes she got?
她有多少雙鞋子?
She got about... 125.
她大概有... 125雙吧.
- A hundred twenty-five pairs of shoes?  - Yeah.
- 125雙鞋子?  - 是的.
Put them in a line from the blacks  all the way to the whites.
要讓黑人和白人之間站成一排
And I'll tell you what. Next time  there's a light on in an empty room,
我告訴你.下一次如果再讓我發現  房間裏沒人還開著燈
I will fire every sorry son of a bitch  in this house. I mean it, Cecil!
我會開除這個房子裏的不負責任的婊子養的  我是認真的，塞西爾
Go back to Texas and run the country  from a dirt shack if I have to.
如果有必要的話，我會回去德州從一個骯髒的  小棚屋開始著手管理這個國家
Is that what you want?
那是你所希望的嗎?
Who do you think pays the  goddamned bills around here?
你覺得是誰在這裏支付這些該死的賬單?
Idon%,butyou  know what I mean.
我才不會呢，但是你明白我的意思
Yes, sir.
是的，先生.
Oh, yeah, I almost forgot.
噢，對，我差點忘了
Lady Bird and I want you to have this.
約翰遜夫人和我希望你收下這個
- Matches your eyes.  - Thank you, sir.
- 很襯你的眼睛.  - 謝謝你，總統先生.
- Get it, Gloria.  - Do it, baby.
- 很好，格羅瑞亞  - 快點啦 ,寶貝.
Swim it! Go ahead, Gloria.
搖擺兩下，格羅瑞亞.
- I see you, baby.  - You see me, babe? Put it on.
- 我看到你了，寶貝.  - 你看到我了，寶貝, 快穿上.
Paughs]
Get it, Gloria.
很好，格羅瑞亞.
- Now that's what I'm talking about.  - Get it, girl! Shake it out! Get it!
- 那才是我說的嘛.  - 你們做到了，搖起來!
Negro! Get out here.
黑鬼! 滾出這裏.
Back there stinking up  my bathroom.
把我的洗手間弄得臭哄哄的.
- Oh, Lord.  - Oh, Lord.
- 噢，上帝呀  - 噢，上帝呀
What you doing?
你幹嘛呢?
Hey! Whoo!
哇噢!
What?
搞什麼?
Get you some!
給你來一點!
- You know.  - That's your friend.
- 你知道.  - 那是你的朋友.
Give me my wig!  What's wrong with you?!
把我的假髮還給我!  你有毛病啊?!
- This my good wig!  - Oh, shit!
- 那是我最好的假髮!  - 噢，我靠!
- Sit down.  - We got the spades up.
- 坐下.  - 我們拿到黑桃了（不曉得啥遊戲）.
Brotherjust handling his business.
哥們剛處理完他的事情
He can still do the splits,  I'll tell you.
他仍然可以來個劈叉  我來告訴你吧
James told me  that Dr. King told the president
詹姆斯跟我我說，金博士告訴總統...  （馬丁.路德.金）
that we would be going to the streets  down South for our right to vote.
我們要去街上投選票了.
- Didn't you, baby?  - What?
- 是不是你說的，寶貝?  - 什麼?
Didn't you tell me  that Dr. King told the president
你是不是跟我說了那個金博士告訴總統
that we was going down South  for our right to vote?
我們要去街上投選票了.?
- I ain't make that up.  - Is that what you heard?
- 那不是我編造的吧.  - 你真的聽他們那麼說來著?
That Dr. King ain't no joke,  with his little militant ass.
那個金博士可不會端著他的  那個好鬥的小屁股開玩笑
- She talking too damned much.  - Well, sound like somebody talking.
- 她他媽的說得多了.  - 聽起來好像是某個人在講話
Shut up.
閉嘴.
- Leave my bird alone.  - Well, you know them three kids
- 別欺負我的小鳥.  - 你知道有三個孩子
got killed down there, trying to get  colored folks registered to vote.
在那裏被殺害了,  所以他們想讓黑人去參加投票
That's why I didn't want  Louis to go down there.
那就是為什麼我不想路易斯去那兒的原因
That's what I was  trying to tell you.
那也是我一直想要告訴你的事
You shouldn't have  sent him down there.
你當時就不應該讓他去那裏
- I know.  - He is down there now,
- 我知道  - 但是現在,他已經在那裏了
and there ain't nothing  we can do about it.
而且我們現在對此也無能為力.
The only reason  the president sent the FBI
總統之所以會派遣FBI  唯一原因就是..
is 'cause two of them were white.
他們兩個都是白人.
- Now who told you that?  - Yeah, who told her that?
- 那又是誰告訴你的?  - 對啊，那是誰告訴她的?
It was in one of them colored newspapers  from Baltimore. That all right with you?
那是我從巴爾的摩的一張黑人報紙上看到的  你滿意了嗎
See, she getting smart now.
你瞧，她現在變聰明了
Honey, you think the president  ought to do something
親愛的, 你覺得總統是不是應該
- about the Voting Rights bill?  - That ain't the trump.
- 就選舉權法案做點兒什麼?  - 那又不是王牌.
President Johnson  just passed the greatest piece
約翰遜總統剛剛從通過了一項..
of civil rights legislation  since Lincoln freed the slaves.
自林肯總統廢除奴隸制以來  最大的民權法案
It's gonna be very difficult to  pass another bill anytime soon.
要在如此短的時間內通過  另外一項法案肯定會非常困難
- That's it.  - You see how my wife quizzes me?
- 就是那麼回事  - 你們看到我老婆是如何盤問我的了吧?
- I get it every day.  - Only, you got to know
- 我每天都接受這種盤問.  - 但是你必須要知道
how much to say,  when you cross the line.
什麼能說什麼不能說...  一定不能越界.
You deal with your woman,  I'll deal with mine.
你處理好你老婆的事  我來處理我老婆的事
At least you tell your wife  what's going on over there.
最起碼你會告訴你老婆  那裏究竟發生了什麼事
- A!  - Aces!  - Damn!
- 靠!
Can't be a king  in your own castle.
可惜你在你自己的城堡裏都不能稱王
You hit the strip joint,  that's what I say.
！@#￥%……&打撲克的說法,  我早就跟你說了
Hey, uh, Glo. Did you hear about  your neighbor, Howard?
喂，格羅瑞亞，  你有沒有聽說過你的鄰居霍華德
Guy down on 8th Street,  caught him in bed with his wife.
他跟一個住在8街的女人廝混的時候  被她的男人逮了個正著
Shot him dead.
然後...頭部中了搶.
- Shot him in the back.  - That's it. That's all of it.
- 是從他後面開槍的.  - 得了，別再說了.
I don't know, maybe he got  what he deserved.
我不知道，也許那是他自己作的.
You sorry sap asses  got to realize
你們這些傻貨們應該要意識到
the Negro ain't gonna take it no more.
黑鬼不能在繼續這樣下去了
This entire country is a tinderbox.
現在整個國家到處危機四伏
Goddamn tinderbox of nigger rage  just waiting to explode!
那些該死的怒火中燒的黑鬼們隨時都會爆發
Now, I want you all  to get on the phone,
現在, 我希望你們全部都待在電話邊上
call the NAACP, CORE  and whoever else
打電話給有色人種促進協會，種族平等大會等等
will listen to your sorry asses
總之就是找那些能聽得進去你們說話的組織
and help me keep them Negroes  off the street.
幫助我把那些黑鬼們從街上弄走
Buck, I smell your ass from here!  What the hell are you waiting for?!
巴克, 我聞到你的臭屁股的味兒了!  你他奶奶的還在等什麼呢?!
Jesus Christ.
上帝呀
Cecil, get me some of  that goddamned prune juice.
塞西爾，給我拿點兒該死的西梅汁來.
I'm not sure what to make  of Malcolm X.
我拿不定主意究竟該拿那個  馬爾科姆.艾克斯怎麼辦（美國黑人領袖）
I know what to make of him.
我知道他究竟在搞什麼
Got a better plan  in place than Dr. King.
他有一個比馬丁路德金更好的計劃
If someone puts their hands on  you, put them in the cemetery.
如果有人將他們的手伸向你  那麼就送他們進墓地裏吧
- That a better plan?  - Ooh, We fixin' to go.
- 那就是所謂的更好的計劃?  - 我們準備要走了.
Bye, Claramay.
拜,凱拉美.
- Good night.  - Good night.
- 晚安.  - 晚安.
I mean...
我是說...
You just mad 'cause he was  talking about your daddy.
你生氣是因為他提到了你爸爸，是嗎
What?
什麼?
He was saying all that  stuff about house Negroes.
他提到了很多有關做屋內服務的黑鬼的問題
I saw you get mad.
我看到你生氣了.
My dad is not a house Negro.
我爸爸不是做屋內服務的黑鬼.
- He a butler, ain't he?  - Don't talk about my dad.
- 他是個男僕, 不是嗎?  - 別跟我提我爸.
I don't talk about your dad,  all right?
我也沒提你爸，對嗎?
That's 'cause my daddy's  proud of what I'm doing.
那是因為我所做的一切  我爸爸都會覺得很驕傲
You all right?
你沒事吧?
Everybody went to church to  raise money for the kids down in Selma.
在塞爾瑪市,所有人都前往教堂為孩子們籌款
But I didn't go. I wasn't gonna give  money to pay for my son to be killed.
但是我沒有去. 我不想把錢捐給他們  好讓他們害死我兒子
Once again, them kids got beat.
那些孩子們又一次失敗了.
This one was so bad that the press  called it "Bloody Sunday."
這是一次慘痛的事件，新聞報道將之稱為 "血色星期天"
They barely left Selma.
他們只有少數幾個人塞爾瑪市  （參見1961年的塞爾瑪大橋事件）
They marched in small groups  through the city of Selma
一個小型的遊行隊伍穿過塞爾瑪市中心
- and were not stopped...  - ...mortars and rockets...
- 沒有被阻止...  - ... 迫擊炮和火箭筒...
...can pound Con Thien  around the clock
...在對康天進行日以繼夜地  （越南美軍基地）
with devastating effect.
進行毀滅性的炮火打擊.
And our ground troops  cannot go into...
我們的地面部隊無法進入...
...it was a different story.
...這是一個完全不同的故事.
Mounted sheriff's deputies  helped to break up the column.
騎警協助驅散遊行的人群.
Once the line was broken...
遊行隊伍曾一度被衝散...
How are your boys, Cecil?
你的兒子們怎麼樣，塞西爾?
I don't know how my oldest is,  Mr. President.
我不太瞭解我大兒子的情況,  總統先生.
I believe he might  be in Selma.
我相信他可能也在塞爾瑪市
And, you know,  sometime I feel like
而且，你知道  有時候我覺得
we're living in  two different worlds.
我跟他，就好像生活在  截然不同的兩個世界裏
Just want to keep him safe.
我只是希望他能安然無恙
...marchers were  treated for tear gas burns,
...遊行隊伍被催淚瓦斯燒傷,
open wounds and broken bones.
裸露的傷口和骨折
One hospital treated...
被送去醫院進行治療...
Every American citizen  must have an equal right to vote.
每一個美國公民都有平等的權利去投票
Yet the harsh fact is that  in many places in this country,
儘管，在這個國家的很多地方  還存在著嚴峻的不公的事實
men and women  are kept from voting
人們無法進行投票
simply because they are Negroes.
其原因僅僅是因為他們是黑鬼.
"Negroes?"
"黑鬼?"
Since when did he start  calling us Negroes?
他是從什麼時候開始叫我們黑鬼的?
That nigger uses the word  "nigger" more than I use it.
那個黑鬼用這個詞的頻率比我還高
But really it's all of us...
但是說真的，我們所有人...
...who must overcome  the crippling legacy
...必須要解決這一極其不公正的....
of bigotry and injustice.
造成了嚴重後果的歷史遺留問題
And we shall overcome.
我們一定會做到的.
First,  a barrage of cover fire,
起初是接二連三的火力壓制,
and then a charge across the street.
發起了一次衝鋒.
The Marines moved out from  the fortified Army compound
海軍陸戰隊開始
blitzed by the original attack.
進行閃電襲擊
Hey, hey, LBJ!
嘿，嘿, LBJ!（LBJ=約翰遜總統）
How many kids  did you kill today?!
你今天殺了多少個孩子?!
Hey,hey,LBJ!
嘿，嘿, LBJ!
How many kids  did you kill today?!
你今天殺了多少個孩子?!
...the ancient imperial city.
...古老的皇城.
It is to Vietnamese  what old Boston is to Americans,
它對越南人的意義就相當於  波士頓對於美國人的意義
where many of its country's  leaders are born or educated.
國家的許多領導者出生於那裏  或者在那裏接受教育
I wish they'd shut up.
我希望他們能閉嘴.
The first sniper shots ricochet  around the thick walls of the building,
狙擊槍的子彈穿過了這所建築厚厚的牆壁
taking the first casualties  of the first squad.
小組有一名士兵死亡
The snipers may be  only two or three,
可能一共有2名或者3名阻擊手
invisible to the buildings  beyond the wall.
躲在牆壁後的某個地方.
But there is also a machine gun  down the street to the left.
在街道左面還有一架重機槍.
Dr. King, you might want to  lie down with that fever.
金博士，也許你也想發燒躺個幾天吧
President Johnson is making  a tragic error in Vietnam.
約翰遜總統在越南犯了一個悲劇性的錯誤
Move over, big yellow.
挪開點兒, 大PP.
Why shouldn't we fight in Vietnam?
為什麼我們不去越南打仗?
The Vietcong don't call us  "niggers," for one.
最起碼，越共不會叫我們黑鬼
Seriously, how many of  your parents support the war?
認真點說，你們的父母中有多少人會支持戰爭?
Well, my Lord.  Why do your parents support it?
我的上帝呀.  為什麼你們的父母會支持戰爭呢?
We haven't spoken about it specifically,  I just know they do.
我們並沒有很明確地談過  但是我知道他們會支持的
Well, what do your daddy do?
你爸爸是做什麼的?
He's a butler.
他是一名男僕
The black domestic play an  important role in our history.
黑人傭人在我們的歷史中扮演著非常重要的角色
I didn't tell you that  to make fun of me.
我跟你說那個，並不是讓你取笑我的.
Young brother, the black  domestic defy racial stereotypes
兄弟，黑人傭人一直在以他們辛勤工作的態度
by being hardworking and trustworthy.
和可以信賴的忠誠  在對抗種族偏見
He slowly  tears down racial hatred
他在以他的強烈的職業道德和  高貴的品格
with his example of a strong work ethic  and dignified character.
逐漸地駁斥和瓦解著所謂的種族仇恨
Now, while we perceive the butler  or the maid to be subservient,
現在，我們在批評那些男僕和女僕們  屈從的態度
in many ways, they are subversive,  without even knowing it.
在許多方面，他們的確是很順從  但那是一種無意識的順從
- Come in, Cecil.  - Afternoon, Mr. Warner.
- 請進，塞西爾.  - 下午好，沃納先生.
Thank you for seeing me.
謝謝您能見我.
Since the colored...
因為有色...
...the black staff
...因為黑人員工
does just as much work  as the white staff,
所做的工作和白人員工所做同樣多,
I believe that our salaries  should reflect our service, sir.
我相信我們的薪水應該也能  體現在我們的服務上面，先生
"Black" staff?
黑人員工?
I also feel  that we should have...
而且我也覺得我們應該能有...
...opportunities of advancement.
...升職的機會.
No black houseman
從來沒有任何一名黑人男僕
has ever been promoted  to the engineer's office.
被提拔為技術人員.
You're very well liked here, Cecil.
塞西爾，看起來你非常喜歡這裏.
But if you're unhappy  with your salary or position,
但如果你對你的薪水和職位不滿意
then I suggest you seek  employment elsewhere.
那我建議你去其他地方找工作吧
- With all due respect...  - Don't let that Martin Luther King shit
- 恕我冒昧...  - 別讓那個馬丁路德金的狗屁言論
fill your britches out.  Just remember where I found you.
搞得你頭腦發熱.  別忘記了我是從哪兒找到你的
Yes, sir.
是的，先生.
Excuse me.
抱歉.
Dr. Martin Luther King,  the apostle of non-violence
馬丁.路德.金博士,  和平與非暴力的民權運動的倡導者
in the civil rights movement has been  shot to death in Memphis, Tennessee.
在田納西州孟菲斯市遭遇槍擊身亡
Police have issued  an All Points Bulletin
警方已經發佈了全面通緝兇犯的通告
for a well-dressed, young white  man seen running from the scene.
目擊者聲稱有一名衣著考究的年輕白人男子  匆匆離開案發現場
Officers also reportedly  chased and fired on
據報道，警官曾經追捕一輛  安裝有無線電裝備的車輛
a radio-equipped car  containing two white men.
車內載有兩名白人男子  並且警方曾向該車輛開火.
I didn't know if I was  gonna get home alive.
我不知道我是否能活著回到家.
It was the first time I felt like  I didn't belong in my own neighborhood.
這是我頭一次覺得  我並不屬於我居住的那個社區.
The whole world was changing,
整個世界都變了
and I didn't know where I fit in.
我也不知道適合我的地方在哪裏
Dr. King has been a buffer  the last two years,
過去的兩年裏，馬丁路德金博士的身份一直是一名男僕
between the black community  and the white community.
他一直遊走於白人社區和黑人社區之間
The white people do not know it,
白人並不知道他是誰
but the white people's  best friend is dead.
但是白人最好的朋友死了
The black people's leader, our Moses,
黑人的領路人，我們的摩西
the once in a four-  or five-hundred year leader,
幾百年來我們唯一的領路人,
has been taken from us  by hatred and bitterness.
也因為痛苦和憎恨  離開了我們
Even as I stand at this hour,
即使是此時此刻，我站在這裏
I cannot even allow hate  to enter my heart at this time,
我都無法允許仇恨涌進我的心中
for it was sickness,  not meanness, that killed him.
因為仇恨是一種病態的心理.
Ma... my room's pink.
媽媽... 我的房間是粉色的.
Make sure you get some more  of my sweet potatoes, Carol.
你得多吃點我做的白薯，卡蘿爾.
I use orange juice  when I make 'em,
我在裏邊加了橙汁,
that's what make 'em so... tart.
那會讓它們吃起來有股酸酸的味道.
How long y'all been dating?
你們倆在一起多久了?
- Five years.  - We're just friends.
- 5年了.  - 我們倆只是朋友而已.
Is, uh,  all the rest of the students
噢，其餘的學生們
are they getting involved  in politics, too?
他們也都參與政治活動嗎?
There's been a division.  Kind of a split, Ma.
我們都有各自的分工  我們現在有一點點分裂,媽媽
A few of them,  like John Lewis, they're still...
他們中的幾個，比如約翰.路易斯  他們還在...
- I love John Lewis.  - How you know who John Lewis is?
- 我喜歡約翰.路易斯.  - 你怎麼知道約翰.路易斯是誰?
'Cause, honey,  I read Jet magazine.
因為，親愛的，我有讀JET雜誌
I'm not just sitting up there  sewing for you all day.
我又不是整天坐在這裏  就知道給你縫縫補補
Ooh.
噢.
I'm sick and tired of getting  thrown in jail.
我已經厭倦了待在監獄裏的日子.
Yeah, well, that makes  two of us, don't it?
嗯，我也一樣
Dr. King's philosophy ultimately  got him murdered.
金博士的人生觀最終  導致了他被謀殺
It worked when we started,
當我們剛剛開始起步的時候  他的那一套很有用
but... now it's time to take  the next step, which is politics.
但是... 現在已經是時候進行下一步行動了  這就是政治
So y'all going  to the White House now?
所以，你們都要去白宮?
Daddy, Louis going  to the White House.
爸爸，路易斯要去白宮
You know they ain't gonna  let you in there
你知道他們不會讓你進去那裏的
with them nipples out.
尤其是你還穿著那種袒胸露乳的衣服
Maybe one, but not both of 'em.
也許你們中的一個人可以進去  但是肯定不會讓你們兩個都進不去
Shut up. Nah, we're...  we're more grass roots.
閉嘴. 我們...  我們大部分都是草根平民.
One-on-one with the community.
我們可以直接跟所有成員聯絡.
Although we have started  our own political party.
雖然我們已經成立了我們自己的政黨
What's your party?
你的政黨是什麼?
You like to party?
你喜歡派對?（Party 雙關語）
I like to party.  What's your party called?
我喜歡派對  你的派對叫什麼?
The Black Panther Party.
黑豹黨.（一個左翼黑人民權組織）.
What kind of name is that?  What's that stand for?
那是什麼名字啊?  那表示什麼意義?
We... provide free breakfast  for children,
我們... 為孩子們提供免費的早餐
free medical clinics, free clothing,  self-defense classes.
免費的醫療診所, 免費的衣物,  我們還提供自我防禦課程.
And why y'all need self-defense?
為什麼你們需要自我防禦?
We ain't gettin' beat no more.
我們不會再被他們打敗了
Me and your daddy saw a  wonderful movie the other night.
前幾天我和你爸爸  看了一個很棒的電影.
Reminded me so much of you.
那電影讓我想起很多有關你的事
Oh, yeah?
是嗎?
What was the name  of that movie, honey?
親愛的，那電影叫什麼名字來著?
In the Heat of the Night.
炎熱的夜晚  （第40屆奧斯卡金像獎最佳影片）
In the Heat... of the Night,  with Sidney Poitier.
炎熱的... 夜晚,  是西德尼·波蒂埃演的吧.
Lord, Sidney Poitier.  I love Sidney Poitier.
天哪，是西德尼·波蒂埃.  我喜歡西德尼·波蒂埃.
Sidney Poitier's a white man's fantasy  of what he wants us to be.
西德尼·波蒂埃就是白人們的理想人物  他們希望我們都變成西德尼·波蒂埃那樣
But his movies have him  fighting for equal rights.
但是在他的電影中，他也在為了平等權在奮鬥
Only in a way that's acceptable  to the white status quo.
但那種平等只是建立在接受  目前這種以白人主導一切的現狀的前提之上
- Ah.  - The brother can't act.
- 噢.  - 可那是行不通的.
What are you talking about?
你說什麼呢?
He just won the Academy Award.
他剛剛贏得了奧斯卡金像獎.
He's breaking down barriers  for all of us.
他為我們所有人打開了一道屏障
By being white.  By acting white.
那只是以白人的方式而已
Sidney Poitier is nothing but  a rich Uncle Tom.
西德尼·波蒂埃只是一個有錢的湯姆叔叔而已  除此之外他什麼都不是
Look at you.
看看你自己.
All puffed up.
一幅自負的、憤憤不平的樣子
With your hat on your head.
還戴著那麼一頂奇形怪狀的帽子.
Coming in here,  saying whatever you want.
回到這裏,  滿嘴跑火車.
Girlfriend belching at the table.
女朋友還在飯桌上直打嗝
You don't even feel  you gotta go to school,
即使是拿著我給你的錢
even though I gave you the money.
你都沒覺得你應該回去上學
You need to go.
你該走了
Yeah, Louis.  I need you to get out of my house.
是的，路易斯  請你離開我的房間
- What?  - Get the hell out of my house!
- 你說什麼?  - 你給我滾出我的房間!
- What are you doing?  - Get on out!
- 你在做什麼?  - 滾出去!
- He's gotta go!  - No, Cecil, no!
- 他必須得離開!  - 不，塞西爾，不要!
- I can't take this no more!  - We ain't seen this boy!
- 我再也無法忍受這一切了!  - 我們不會再見到他了!
We ain't seen this boy!
我們不會再見到他了!
I'm gonna snatch the life  out of you, boy!
以後你的生活跟我無關
- Now, everybody just sit down.  - I'm sorry, Mr. Butler,
- 現在，大家都坐下  - 我很抱歉，男僕先生
I didn't mean to make  fun of your hero.
我並不是故意要取笑你的英雄.
Everything you are and  everything you have is...
你的生命，以及你所擁有的一切...
...'cause of that butler.
...都是那個男僕給你的.
Now you take that trifling  low-class bitch...
現在，帶著你那位輕浮的品質低劣的婊子...
...and get out of this house.
...滾出這所房子.
I like Sidney Poitier, Daddy.
爸爸，我喜歡西德尼·波蒂埃.
What's that movie he did?  Look Who's Coming to Dinner?
他演的那部電影叫什麼來著?  看看誰來吃晚飯了?
Everything ain't a joke.
別開玩笑了.
- Carol came to dinner.  - Hush, Charlie.
- 卡蘿爾來吃晚餐了.  - 噓，查理.
Police took Louis the next day.
第二天，警察帶走了路易斯.
Y'all gonna make me late for work.
你們要害我遲到了.
Unc, I'm sorry.
嗯，對不起
Who else I'm supposed to call  to bail him out?
我還能找誰來保釋他出去呢?
What they got him in for this time?  Sit up!
這次他們又是為了什麼把他抓進來的?  坐起來!
Louis said they  stopped him just because.
路易斯說他們抓他是因為
Just because.
因為.
He said he wasn't going  to get beat no more, so...
他說他不會再被打敗了，所以...
...he got out the car  and he hit 'em back.
...他下了車，並且回擊了他們
What about that little gal of his?
那他的那位小妞呢?
They put her in the hospital.
他們送她去了醫院
The hospital.
醫院
Charlie.
查理.
This shit's gotta stop, man.
這些破事必須得停止了.
I'm late for work.
我上班要遲到了
You tell Louis I'm not his mama.
你轉告路易斯，我不是他媽.
I want my money back.
而且我希望拿回我的錢
You all right?
你沒事吧?
Yeah, I'm all right.
嗯，我沒事.
Thanks, Uncle Carter.
謝謝, 卡特叔叔
You need to take all this Black  Panther shit somewhere else.
你必須得帶著你的那些  狗屁黑豹黨的東東去其他地方
Now, I'm not them.  I want my money back, hear me?
現在，我要你把我的錢還給我，你聽到了嗎?
- Yes, sir.  - Every dime.
- 是的，先生  - 每一分錢.
- Yes, sir.  - Hey, Unc... don't tell Daddy.
- 是的，先生.  - 喂，叔叔，別告訴我爸爸.
How you avoid all that sex  in prison?
在監獄裏你是如何避開那些性行為的?
Do they teach you that  with the Panthers?
那個什麼黑豹黨有沒有教你那些事?
They teach you how to... to sit...
他們教你如何坐......
- She been drinking again?  - No. She's sober.
- 她又開始喝酒了嗎?  - 沒有，她很清醒.
She ain't doing nothing but sewing  and feeding them damn fishes.
她一天到晚什麼都不幹，除了做縫紉工作  和餵養她的那些魚
Feed them more than she feed me.
餵給它們的比餵給我的還多.
You excited about  going back to Howard?
回去霍華德是不是讓你很興奮?
Excited about not going back.
我很興奮因為我不用再回去那裏了.
- What?  - Yeah.
- 什麼?  - 是的.
I'm going to Vietnam.
我要去越南啦.
Charlie, don't do this.  Don't do this.
查理，不要那麼做  不要那麼做.
- This country treats us like dogs!  - And do what? Don't do this?
- 這個國家對待我們就像是狗一樣!  - 那麼做什麼，做這事兒?
You fight your country.
你在為你的國家而戰
I want to fight for my country.
而我想要為我的國家而戰.
- I won't go to your funeral.  - Good.
- 我不會去參加你的葬禮.  - 很好.
'Cause I don't want you there  with all of that...
因為我也不想讓你穿著那些亮晶晶的...
...black leather and latex,
...奇裝異服出現在我的葬禮上
shining and taking away the attention  off of my pretty face in my casket.
吸引走那些原本應該停留在  我的英俊的臉蛋兒的注意力
What do they call you now, Louise?
他們現在怎麼稱呼你, 路易斯?
- Shut up.  - Louise Gaines.
- 閉嘴.  - 路易斯 蓋恩斯.
Charlie, shut up.
查理，閉嘴.
I want to know every goddamn  domestic policy decision right now,
我需要馬上知道每一項該死的國內政策,
and I want it on the table right now.
我要讓他們立刻出現在我的書桌上.
- OK.  - OK.
- 好的.  - 好的
Did you get  the memos we sent last week?
你收到上周我們寄給你的備忘錄了嗎?
John and I strongly agree  that the time calls for...
約翰和我強烈贊同...
A goddamn fly,  a goddamn fly in here.
一隻該死的蒼蠅,  這裏有一隻該死的蒼蠅.
- Jesus Christ.  - John and I both think
- 天哪.  - 約翰和我都認為
that the time calls for  a period of benign neglect.
現在需要採取善意忽視的策略.
- Benign neglect.  - Yes.
- 善意忽視?  - 是的.
I like that. I like that.
我喜歡那個.我喜歡那個.
You know, the pigs in the  media describe us as terrorists.
你知道, 媒體的那些豬們  都把我們描述成恐怖分子了
A terrorist is one who  terrorizes and frightens others.
恐怖份子是指那些恐嚇和威脅他人的人
We the ones getting terrorized.
我們才是被恐嚇的人.
How can we exist in, in peace,
當我們在大街上在商店裏  都不敢講話的時候
when we scared to walk  down the street to the store?
我們如何才能和平共處呢
All right, there's this whole black  power movement going on, right?
好，現在的黑人權利運動正在進行，對嗎?
- Right.  - What if we, um...
- 對.  - 假如我們...
What if Nixon promotes black power
假如尼克松決定推動和提升黑人的權利
to mean "black businesses"  and we find ways to support
我是說，支持黑人企業家  只要我們找到合適的支持他們的方式
black entrepreneurs, pass the buck  on desegregation to the courts.
而把廢除種族歧視的責任推卸給法院
Push black enterprise
那將可以使我們贏得20%的選票
to win the 2O percent  of the votes it could swing our way.
而且會打破目前這種僵持的局面
- Excellent, sir.  - Absolutely.
- 這招太高了，先生.  - 絕對的.
You don't know if your ceiling gonna  cave in 'cause your slum lord
你永遠都不知道你的頂棚什麼時候會塌  因為你的平民窟老闆...
too busy running around  collecting rent checks.
正在忙著四處收取他的房租支票呢
But he won't fix your roof.
他不會幫你修理你的屋頂
It's time we take a stand  against these injustices
現在是時候該表明立場和採取行動
that have plagued our community.
來對抗這些已困擾我們很久了的不公.
They take one of ours,  we taking two of theirs.
他們抓走我們中的一個人  那我們就要抓走他們中的兩個人.
- That's right.  - It's been time.
- 對.  - 現在是時候了.
We just need to make sure  that Nixon black power
我們只需要確定  所謂的尼克松黑人權利
doesn't equate Nixon  with the Black Panthers.
並不等於尼克松 + 黑豹黨
Have you lost your mind, man?  Did you read Hoover's last memo on that?
你瘋了嗎?  你沒有讀過胡佛的上一個備忘錄?
- That's my point.  - Goddamn terrifying.
- 那就是我說的重點.  - 太可怕了.
No, no, no. I gave him the green light  to gut those sons of bitches.
不不不. 我已經給他開了一路綠燈  讓他去找出那些婊子養的黑豹黨
- Good.  - Good. Absolutely.
- 很好.  - 絕對的.
No, round 'em all up and  throw 'em down an elevator shaft.
要把他們都弄在一起  然後把它們都丟進升降機井.
I don't proclaim to know everything.  But I promise you...
我不會說我無所不知.  但是我向你們保證..
...they'll always beware  of the nigger with a gun.
...他們總是很懼怕拿著槍的黑鬼
Will there be anything else,  Mr. President?
還有其他事嗎, 總統先生?
How many kids we got coming  to the breakfast tomorrow morning?
明天早晨我們要帶多少孩子去餐館?
Got about 25 to 3O coming.
大概25至30個吧.
Twenty-five to 3O kids  will be able to go to school
這25至30個孩子本來可以去學校
and focus on their lessons.
專心上課.
'Cause they don't want us  to be able to feed our kids.
但因為他們不想讓我們有能力養活我們的孩子
They don't want us  to be able to protect ourselves.
因為他們不想讓我們有能力保護我們自己
What are we doing here?
我們在這裏做什麼?
Thought this was going to be  our community service.
我以為我們是在做我們的社區服務
This is community service.
這就是社區服務.
"Someone kills one of ours,  we kill two of theirs?"
"有人殺了我們中的一個,  我們要殺了他們中的兩個?"
Community protection.
這是社區保護.
Are you ready to kill somebody, Carol?
你準備好去殺人了嗎, 卡蘿爾?
'Cause I ain't.
因為我還沒有準備好
I am.
我準備好了
Did you ever love me, baby?
你有沒有愛過我，寶貝?
Today, a day after police  shot it outwith the Black Panthers,
今天， 在警察和黑豹黨交火後的第二天
killing two of them,  they raided the apartment...
警察又擊斃了兩名黑豹黨成員  他們包圍了黑豹黨成員的公寓...
...the shooting of 26  Panthers in the past year,
...過去一年裏，警方一共擊斃了26名黑豹黨成員
may represent a national campaign  by police to wipe out the Panthers...
這可能也表示警方將會
...the criminal reaction  of the occupants in shooting
在全國範圍對黑豹黨進行徹底地剿滅
at announced police officers,
警方也宣佈了......
emphasizes the extreme viciousness  of the Black Panther Party.
並且強調指出黑豹黨....
"Party ls a Groovy Thing"]
- Hey, baby-  - Hey.
- 嗨，寶貝  - 嗨.
- Happy birthday.  - Happy birthday to me, huh?
- 生日快樂.  - 祝我生日快樂呀?
Happy birthday to you.
祝你生日快樂.
Right now, this is the present  I want, right here.
此時此刻, 我想要的生日禮物就在這裏
Well, you want it right here?
噢，你現在就想要嗎?
Mm-mm, you know right...
嗯，你知道的...
- Right here?  - Kids up... Kids down...?
- 就在這裏?  - 孩子在樓上還是在樓下...?
Ain't no kids in the house no more.
這所房子裏再也有沒有孩子了
Hey, I made you a birthday cake.
我給你做了一隻生日蛋糕.
I got all the cake  I want right here.
我想吃的蛋糕就在這裏啦.
No, you crazy.
不要啦，你個瘋子.
I got some champagne  cooling in the icebox.
我準備了一些香檳  正在冷凍室冰鎮著呢
And some ice cream, too.  Get some ice cream.
還有一些冰淇淋  要吃點嗎
You gonna be drinking with me?
你要跟我一起喝嗎?
You know I don't drink.
你知道我不喝酒的.
I don't drink.
我不喝酒
Just playing with you.
我是在逗你玩啦
I just want to see you move  a little bit. Go ahead.
我想看你扭幾下，快點兒啦.
' 9h, my God!
噢，天哪!
We get any mail  from Charlie today?
今天有沒有收到查理的來信?
No.
沒有
- No?  - Haven't heard from Charlie.
- 沒有?  - 查理一直沒有音訊.
I know. I got an idea.
我知道. 我有個主意.
I think we should go  to Shantay's tonight.
我覺得今晚我們應該去Shantay跳舞
Oh, no.  No, I'm too old for disco.
噢，不. 我都這把年紀了  已經不適合去跳迪斯科了
We not old. Come on. We ain't old.
我們還不老啦，走吧.  我們還沒那麼老.
I just don't feel like  doing no disco.
我只是不想去跳迪斯科
Our boys are gone.  It's just you and me.
我們的兒子們走來  現在只剩下你和我
You and me, we are free.  I forgot this. I forgot this.
你和我，我們倆現在自由了  噢，我都忘記這個東東了
Now, look at us.  Little happy birthday present.
現在，看著這個小小的生日禮物
I want you to go put it on, upstairs.
我想讓你上樓去換上它
- Put it on?  - Yeah. Go put it on.
- 穿上?  - 對，去穿上.
- All right.  - Make it snappy.
- 好吧.  - 迅速點.
Bring down my sewing kit,  'cause I need to do some alterations.
順便把我的針線包拿下來  可能我得幫你改一改
Make it snappy!
迅速點!
Hello.
你好.
Hi. Where are you?
嗨，你在哪兒?
Where?
哪裏?
You should call me back,  because this is not a good time.
你應該回頭再打給我  因為現在這個時間不太合適
- He's home again.  - It fit!
- 他在家.  - 很合適呀!
- We gonna go on out tonight.  - Where?
- 今晚我們要出去咯.  - 哪兒?
- He's home and...  - Boy, you good, aren't you?
- 他在家，而且...  - 你還好吧?
- You all right?  - Who that?
- 你沒事吧?  - 那是誰?
Call me back.
回頭打給我.
- OK?  - Oh, it's Louis.
- 好嗎?  - 噢，是路易斯呀.
He asking for some money?
他又打電話來要錢?
Hey, Louis.
嗨，路易斯
I didn't expect to hear  from you on my birthday.
我過生日的時候可沒指望你打電話來
You should feel  ashamed of yourself.
你應該為自己感到羞恥.
You're a grown-ass man calling  your mama, asking for money.
你現在是個成年人了  居然還打電話跟你媽媽要錢
And guess what?  It's the butler's money.
你猜猜怎麼著?  這可都是男僕先生的錢.
It's Uncle Tom's money.
是湯姆叔叔的錢
And he ain't giving  none out today.
而且，今天他一個子兒都不會給你的
Bye.
拜
I got it.
我明白了
You got the wrong house.
你找錯地方了.
It's the wrong house.
你好錯地方了.
翻譯： @ 塔拉Tala
Vietnam took my boy,
越南帶走了我的兒子
and I didn't understand why we  were there in the first place.
打一開始我就不明白為什麼我們要去那裏
Your father still alive, Cecil?
你爸爸還活著嗎 ,塞西爾 ?
No, sir.
沒有，先生
My father died when I was a child.
我還是孩子的時候他就死了
Is there anything else that you  would like, Mr. President?
你還想要點什麼嗎，總統先生?
Yeah. Come sit.
對，過來坐下.
Sit down, you know?
請坐, 你知道嗎?
There's been a lot of talk  of me resigning and...
最近一段時間，有關讓我辭職下台...
...things of that nature,  but I just want you to know
...等等這類說法比比皆是  但是我只想讓你知道
it's never gonna happen.
那是絕對不會發生的.
I'm gonna come out of this thing  stronger than ever.
經過這事兒，會讓我變得前所未有的強大
Is there anything else  that you would like...
你還想要點兒什麼嗎...
...Mr. President?
...總統先生?
Louis is here, looking for you.
路易斯在這裏, 他在找你.
- Got everybody all worried.  - Well, I finished school.
- 大家都很擔心你.  - 我讀完大學了.
I got my master's  in political science.
我拿到了社會學的碩士學位
Hey! That's what I'm talking about.
哇噢，我就說嘛
Get that education.
要好好讀書.
There he is!  Well, I'm gonna let you all to it.
他來了!  好吧，你們倆好好聊吧.
Ain't no need for that, Carter.
卡特，你不需要離開.
- Hey, Dad.  - Get out of here, Louis.
- 嗨，爸爸  - 離開這裏，路易斯.
- Dad...  - I said leave.
- 爸爸...  - 我說了，你走吧.
Keep doing what you doing.
繼續做好你在做的事
Thank you, Uncle Carter.
謝謝你，卡特叔叔.
Why you do that? Huh?  That was wrong.
為什麼你要那麼做? 啊?  那是不對的.
That boy's hurting, too. He's just  trying to get his act together.
那個孩子也一樣受到了傷害  他只是在設法振作起來.
He should be hurting, Carter.
他應該受到傷害,卡特.
Boy didn't even go  to his own brother's funeral.
他甚至都沒有去參加他弟弟的葬禮.
He's full of shit is what he is.  He ain't doing nothing right.
他就是狗屎一坨  他就沒做對過任何事.
He just got his master's!  What more you want him to do?
他剛剛拿到了他的碩士學位  你還想讓他怎麼樣?
Every gray hair I have  is 'cause of that boy.
我的每一個白頭髮都是為他操心操的
The years started to drift by,
一年又一年，時間緩慢地在流逝,
but the pain in my heart  never went away.
但是深植於我內心深處的痛苦卻從未消失
"You and I Ain't Nothin' No More"]
Through it all,  Louis and I never spoke.
經過了那麼多事以後  我和路易斯再也沒有講過話
As we are a nation under God,  so I am sworn...
因為我們是上帝庇佑下的一個國家,  所以，我發過誓...
Half of our  oil is now imported...
現在，我們有一半石油都依靠進口...
It is a crisis that strikes  at the very hear':
這對每一個人
and soul and spirit  of our national will.
以及我們的國家的精神和靈魂都是一次打擊
- I feel one coming now.  - Not to worry.
- 有人來了.  - 別擔心.
Two of you,  stay home until you feel better.
你們倆個,  待在家裏直到你們感覺好一點再來
OK, Barn, I'll stay.  But I ain't never gonna feel no better.
好的， 巴納，我會帶在家裏  但是那也無法讓我感覺更好
In our district alone,  we have nine percent unemployment.
在我們這個街區  我們有百分之九的人都失業在家.
In the country at large, 14 percent  are living below the poverty line.
在這個廣袤的國家,  還有14%的人生活在貧困線以下
Sixty percent of those  are either black or Hispanic.
而在那些人之中  60%的人不是黑人就是拉丁裔
Now, if I'm voted to Congress,  reducing those figures is gonna be
現在，我首要的目標  就是致力於推動國會投票
one of my primary objectives.
來改善這種情況  降低那些驚人的數據
Yeah?
你好?
Oh, hey.
噢，嗨.
Thanks for getting back to me.
謝謝你回電話給我.
How much did he lose by?
他損失了多少?
Really?
真的嗎?
All right, then.
那好吧.
I appreciate it.
我很感激
No, he didn't win.
沒有，他沒有贏.
I think you should call him.
我想你應該打電話給他
Right after Charlie passed,
查理過世之後,
Louis came over  and paid me a visit.
路易斯過來看過我一次
Hmm.
嗯.
He found me on the kitchen floor.
他發現我躺在廚房的地板上.
I had passed out.
我當時神志不清.
Drunk.
我喝多了
I'd gone to the bathroom  all over myself.
我在衛生間吐得自己全身都是.
He's the one that cleaned me up.
是他幫我清理乾淨那些污物.
And then he told me  I was the best mother
然後他告訴我說  我是世界上最好的...
anybody could ever want.
每個人都嚮往的媽媽
I think, about now...
我想, 現在...
...he'd want to hear from his daddy.
...他一定很想聽到他爸爸的聲音.
I think you ought to call him.
我想你應該打電話給他.
Mm-hm.
嗯
Cecil?
塞西爾?
Yes, sir, Mr. President.
是的，總統先生.
You stay there, I'm coming to you.
你待在那裏，我過去找你.
I... have a...
我... 有一個...
...secret mission for you.
...秘密任務要交給你.
Yes, sir.
好的，先生.
I like to send people  money when they write me
我很想寄一些錢給那些寫信給我...
about their financial problems,
面臨財政問題的人們
but my staff has been  trying to get me to stop.
但是我的職員一直在試著阻止我這麼做.
You think you could  help me to keep this going?
你可以幫助我繼續做這件事嗎?
Absolutely, Mr. President.
沒問題，總統先生.
Well, I appreciate  your help with this.
我很感激你能這麼做.
And, please, don't tell Nancy.
還有，請不要告訴南茜
Of course not.
我不會的.
- Morning, Cecil.  - Morning, Mr. Warner.
- 早上好，塞西爾.  - 早上好，沃納先生
May I sit down?
我可以坐下嗎?
I've been here  for over 2O years now.
到現在為止  我在這裏工作已經超過20年了.
For all that time,  the black help
過去的這些年  黑人員工所拿到的薪水
has been paid a smaller salary  than the white help.
一直比白人員工的薪水低很多
And I just don't think  that's right, Mr. Warner.
我就只覺得這是不對的，沃納先生.
There are black housemen  who should be engineers by now.
現在，這裏有很多黑人男僕  都應該成為工程師
They should've been promoted  years ago.
其實許多年前他們就應該升職了.
You think so?
你這麼認為嗎?
I'm gonna have to be paid  the same as the white help,
我也應該拿到和白人員工同等的薪水
or I'm gonna have to move on.
不然我就只好離開了.
I guess you'll be moving on then.
那我猜你最好還是走人吧.
I told the president  that you'd say that.
我會把你的意思轉達給總統先生.
He told me to tell you  to take this up with him, personally.
他讓我轉告你，他會親自著手處理這事兒的
Excuse me.
我先走了
I'm not comfortable  with all the foreign policy hawks
吉姆，我不喜歡那些提倡強硬的外交政策...
surrounding Ronnie, Jim.
的鷹派人物整天圍著羅尼轉
We need more moderates on his staff.  And a summit with the Russians.
我們需要更多的溫和派成員在他身邊  還有，這次與俄國人的峰會.
Ronnie has to meet  with them face to face
如果我們打算撬動這座冰山
if we're ever  going to thaw this ice.
羅尼就必須要跟他們親自會面
- Cecil.  - Yes, Mrs. Reagan?
- 塞西爾.  - 是，裏根夫人?
We will talk, Jim. Yes.
我們回頭再談，吉姆.
Yes, ma'am?
夫人?
You're very popular around here.
你在這裏非常受歡迎呀.
Everyone says you're the man  that got them raises and promotions.
所有的人都說是你讓他們  得到了升職和加薪的機會
- I had no idea.  - I wish I could take credit for that.
- 我居然都對此全然不知.  - 我希望我能接受這份功勞.
I'd like to invite you  to the State Dinner next week.
我想邀請你參加下周舉行的國宴
- I'm gonna be there, Mrs. Reagan.  - No.
- 我會在那裏的，裏根先生.  - 不
Not as a... Not as a butler, Cecil.  I'm inviting you as a guest.
不是... 不是作為男僕，塞西爾.  我是邀請你作為賓客出席國宴.
But the president prefers  for me to serve him personally.
但是總統先生會更希望我親自為他服務
Don't you worry about, Ronnie.  I'll take care of that.
你別擔心那個，至於羅尼  我會照顧他的
So we'll see you next week.  You and your wife.
那麼我們下周見  請帶上你的夫人.
My Wife?
我夫人?
It's... It's Gloria, yes?
她... 她叫格羅瑞亞, 對嗎?
- Yes, ma'am.  - Yes.
- 對，夫人.  - 嗯
Hmm.
嗯
Here's the Entrance Hall.
這裏是門廳.
Beautiful.
真漂亮.
Can I get you a glass  of champagne, Mr. Gaines?
我可以幫你拿杯香檳嗎, 蓋恩斯先生?
- Shut up.  - Right.
- 閉嘴吧你  - 好的.
Ladies and gentlemen,
女士們先生們,
the President and First Lady  of the United States.
美國總統和第一夫人.
It was different sitting  at the table instead of serving it.
站在這個桌子旁服務  和坐在這裏的感覺是那麼地不同
Real different.
非常不同.
I could see the two faces  the butlers wore to survive.
我可以看到那些男僕們在服務時的  那張與平時完全的痛的臉孔
And I knew I'd lived my life  with those same two faces.
我知道在我的一生中，  我也始終以兩張面孔示人
Gloria looked so happy,  but I didn't feel the same way.
格羅瑞亞看起來很開心  但是我並不覺得.
I guess I wished we were there  for real instead of for show.
我猜我所希望的是，我們能真的坐在那裏  而不是為了作秀
I think that's bon appétit, everybody.
我猜大家都胃口都很好
You black mother...
你娘的...
I want to make myself clear  on this issue.
我想就這個問題表明我自己的態度
If Congress passes sanctions  against South Africa,
如果國會要讓對南非的制裁決議通過
I will be forced to  veto those sanctions.
我將不得不否決這些制裁決議.
Well, Mr. President, we feel  that that would be a major mistake.
總統先生，我們覺得那會是一個絕對的錯誤
The brutal repression  of South African black citizens
南非對黑人平民殘酷鎮壓的行為
makes this no longer  a foreign policy issue,
已經使得這一問題  不再單純停留在外交政策的層面
but a United States racial issue.
而是牽扯到美國對於種族問題的態度
We're senators  from your own party.
我們是屬於你自己的黨派的參議員.
That's why we feel so comfortable  in letting you know
這也是為什麼我們很想讓你知道
that South Africa  is a human rights disaster.
南非現在存在很嚴重的人權問題
Black people are  being beaten, tortured,
黑人常年遭受欺壓和折磨
gunned down  in the middle of the street.
甚至在大街上都會遭到槍擊
Americans see all this on TV,  they're horrified by apartheid.
美國人可以從電視上看到這一切,  種族隔離讓他們感到震驚
I've made my decision.
我已經做出決定了
Mr. President, your reputation  as a world leader is at stake.
總統先生，你作為世界領導者的聲望  已經受到了影響
United States of America needs to be
就種族問題而言...
on the right side of history  on the race issue.
美國需要站在歷史正確的一面
I say again.
我再說一遍.
If Congress passes this bill,
如果國會會通過這個法案,
I Will veto it.
我會提出否定
Peﬂod.
句號.
What? You reading now?
什麼? 你又在讀書?
Get up and do the dishes  'fore I shoot your little ass.
快點起來，在我射飛你的小腦袋之前  快點把這些盤子都洗乾淨.
Nothing seemed right to me  after that State Dinner.
那次晚宴之後  好像我周圍的任何事看起來都不對勁了
Got all confused.
我總是感到很困惑.
They had started writing books
他們開始把那些有關路易斯
about everything Louis  and his friends had done.
和他的朋友們所做的事情  寫成文章，寫成書
Louis was never a criminal.
路易斯不再是一名罪犯.
He was a hero,
他變成了一名英雄,
fighting to save  the soul of our country.
變成了一名為了拯救我們國家的靈魂的鬥士
- Would you like a cookie?  - Thank you, sir.
- 你要來電而餅幹嗎?  - 謝謝你，先生.
- Cookies.  - Thank you.
- 餅乾.  - 謝謝你.
Cookie?
餅乾?
- Thank you.  - Thank you.
- 謝謝你  - 謝謝你
Thank you.
謝謝你
Cookie?
餅乾?
I had always loved sewing.  But just felt different now.
我一直很喜歡我的工作.  但是現在卻覺得有點兒不同
I didn't know that an old man  could feel so lost.
我不知道是不是每一個老人  都會有失落和無助的感覺
That's how I felt.
可是. 我是那麼地失落
那麼地無助
Americans always turned
美國人對於我們對自己人所犯下的錯誤
a blind eye to what we'd done  to our own.
總是採取視而不見的態度
We look out to the world and judge.
卻很喜歡對其他國家的事指手畫腳
We hear about  the concentration camps,
我們聽說了那些集中營的故事,
but these camps went on  for 200 years
但是就在美國，就在我們自己的土地上
right here in America.
這樣的營地卻已經存在了200年之久
Buried my daddy right over there.
我的爸爸就埋葬在那變邊
My mama would've been  right proud of me,
我媽媽一定會以我為榮,
being with a man like you's.
因為我嫁了一個像你這麼好的男人
Taking such good care of me  all of these years.
這麼多年一直那麼照顧我  那麼疼愛我
I love you, Cecil Gaines.
我愛你，塞西爾 蓋恩斯.
I love you more, Gloria.
我更愛你，格羅瑞亞
Are you sure about this?
你確定你要這麼做嗎?
Yes, sir.
是的
I just want to be the one  to tell you first, that's all.
我只是想第一個告訴你
But you're the best butler here.
但是你是這裏最棒的男僕.
You're like family, Cecil.
對我來說，你就像家人一樣，塞西爾
Been an honor serving you.
能服侍你是我的榮幸
Well, not just for me,  I'm sure I speak for all the presidents
不止是我，我可以代表所有的總統說
when I say that you've  served your country well.
你為你的國家提供了最好的服務
Thank you, Mr. President.
謝謝你，總統先生
Cecil?
塞西爾?
This whole civil rights issue...
有關所有的這些民權問題...
I sometimes fear I'm...
有時候我會害怕我...
on the wrong side of it,  that I'm...
站在了錯誤的一面, 嗯....我...
...just wrong.
...做錯了
Sometimes I think I'm just  scared of what it really means.
有時候我覺得我很害怕  那些事情所蘊含的真正的意義
But I'm trying not to be  so scared anymore.
但是我會試著不要再害怕.
- Who do we want to free?!  - Mandela!
- 我們想讓誰獲得自由?!  - 曼德拉!
When do we want him free?
我們想讓誰獲得自由?!
- Now!  - Free Mandela!
- 立刻!  - 釋放曼德拉!!
Twenty years ago, we marched  in this country for our rights.
20年前, 我們在這個國家為爭取我們的權利而遊行
Today, we march to free  the people of South Africa.
今天，我們遊行是為了為南非的同胞爭取自由
Yeah!
對!
Ronald Reagan has attacked or dismantled  every civil rights program
羅納德.裏根在  攻擊和破壞我們的每一項
that has ever been put in place.
正在進行的民權計劃
- Yeah!  - Right!
- 對!  - 對i!
Aiding the oppression of black South  Africans is absolutely consistent
他一直在以他的種族問題的政策來
with his policies on race issues.  Am I right?
協助壓迫南非的黑人  我說的對嗎?
- Am I right?  - Yes!
- 我說得對嗎?  - 對!
Hold on, hold on.
等等，等一下
Excuse me. Steven?  Where's Steven?
斯蒂文，斯蒂文在哪兒?
- Free Mandela!  - Free Mandela, y'all!
- 釋放曼德拉!  - 釋放曼德拉!
Free Mandela!
釋放曼德拉!
Free Mandela!  Free Mandela! Free Mandela!
釋放曼德拉!  釋放曼德拉!釋放曼德拉!
Hi, Dad.
嗨，爸爸
Hi, Louis.
嗨，路易斯
What are you doing here?
你在這裏做什麼?
I came here to protest with you.
我來這裏和你一起抗議.
You'll get arrested, Dad.  You'll lose your job.
你會被逮捕的，爸爸  你會丟了你的工作
I lost you.
我弄丟了你
I'm sorry.
對不起
I'm sorry, son.
對不起，兒子
Don't worry, Dad, we'll be  out of here in a few hours.
別擔心，爸爸  幾個小時後我們就會出去的
Who said I was worried?
誰說我會擔心的?
After going to jail,  I thought I'd seen it all.
我離開監獄以後  我想我已經明白了一切
- You OK, Daddy?  - Yeah, no, no, no. I'm good.
- 你還好嗎，爸爸?  - 嗯，不，不，我沒事.
But I never imagined I'd see...
但是我從未想像過我會見到...
...a black man
...一個黑人
be a real contender for  the President of the United States.
會真的成為一名美國總統的競選人
Here we go.
我們開始吧.
- It's that sweet corn.  - That corn look good.
- 這是甜玉米.  - 那個玉米看上去看不錯.
Gloria and I would walk  to our polling place
每天晚上，格羅瑞亞和我都會  去我們的投票地點...
every night to see where  we'd be voting for Barack Obama.
我們就是在那裏  為貝拉克·奧巴馬投出了我們的選票
We'd just... stare at it, smile.
我們只是坐在那裏, 看著，笑著.
- You done?  - Pretty much.
- 你吃完了嗎?  - 差不多了.
Good. Time to go.
很好，我們該走了
You done pretty good there.
你在照片裏看起來非常棒.
Thanks, honey.
謝謝，親愛的.
How come Louis' wife  named that child...
為什麼路易斯的妻子要給那個孩子取名叫...
- ...Shaquanda?  - Now, don't start that again.
- ... 史曠達?  - 現在可別再提這茬兒了.
I ain't starting it, I just don't know  what kind of name that is.
我又沒提啦, 我只是不太明白  那名字究竟是個啥意思
I mean, really! Shaquanda?
我是說真的啦，史曠達?
I think she done that just to spite me.
我想她起那麼名字可能就是為了氣我
Ain't nobody  done nothing to spite you.
這裏沒有任何人會做任何事來氣你啦.
Yes, she did.
嗯，她肯定是.
She a ugly little old girl, too.  That little pug nose.
她就是一個醜陋的小丫頭  你瞧她那個扁扁的塌鼻子
- I hope she grow out of it.  - Now, you need to stop that.
- 我希望她的鼻子能再長大一點  - 別再嘮叨那個啦.
- You know that ain't right.  - Don't you think
- 你知道你不應該那麼想啦  - 難道你不覺得..
she look a little like  Louis around the mouth?
她的嘴巴有點兒像路易斯?
I think... she look just like you.
我覺得... 她看起來就跟你一樣
- Like me?  - Yeah, so you need to...
- 像我?  - 對，所以你得...
...you need  to stop talking about her.
...你得停止再那麼談論她.
Let me look at her again,  then, real good.
讓我再看看她，嗯，很好
Paughs]
She do look a little bit like me.  She a pretty little thing.
她看起來是有點兒像我.  她是個漂亮的小東西.
I guess I can put up  with the name Shaquanda.
我想我可以接受史曠達這個名字
I forgot where I put my Bible.
我忘了我把我的聖經放哪兒了.
- You know I need my Bible.  - Mm-hm.
- 你知道我需要我的聖經  - 嗯
- I think I left it in the bathroom.  - Why is Louis late?
- 我想我可能把它忘在洗手間了.  - 路易斯為什麼遲到了?
Boy gets elected to Congress...
自從他當選議員之後...
...and he ain't been on time  getting us to church ever since.
...就很少能按時帶我們去教堂了
- I can't believe you still... fussing.  - He gonna be late to his own funeral.
- 我都不敢相信你還在... 發牢騷.  - 我看他連去參加他自己的葬禮都會遲到
Are you still fussing  about Louis?
你還在為路易斯的事... 感到煩躁?
He said he's gonna be here for us.
他說了他會來這裏接我們.
- Go ahead, call him.  - I ain't calling Louis.
- 去吧，打電話給他.  - 我才不會打電話給路易斯.
I'm gonna get my purse and...
我要拿上我的錢包，還有...
What'd you say? Isaiah?
你說什麼? 以賽亞書?（聖經舊書）
I see you got... your mark here.
我看到你.. 在這裏做了標記.
I'm gonna fall all over myself.
這玩意得把我絆倒在地
Baby, you need...  to move that to the other side.
寶貝，你得...  把它挪到另一邊.
Baby?
寶貝?
Honey?
親愛的?
You sleeping?
你睡著了?
Baby?
寶貝?
Are you all right?
你還好嗎?
...states will be closing,
...投票站即將關閉,
and there are some big ones,  especially California,
那些都是勝算比較大的州,  特別是加利福尼亞
the largest state  in the United States,
加州美國最大的州,
with 55 electoral votes.
擁有55張選票.
Hawaii, that's where  Barack Obama was born.
在夏威夷州, 那是巴拉克·奧巴馬出生的地方
will be closing its polls.
那裏的投票站也即將關閉.
Idaho, Oregon  and Washington state,
愛達荷, 俄勒岡，還有華盛頓州
and those states  have been going Democratic
最近幾年，這些州在總統競選的過程中
in presidential contests  in recent years.
始終在堅持推行民主競選
So in a few seconds
那麼馬上
those states  will be closing their polls,
這些州也即將關閉他們的投票站
and presumably we'll  be able to see what's...
我們大致可以推測出...
Louis!
路易斯!
...a major projection at that point.
...這是一個預測.
This is a moment that a lot of  people have been waiting for...
這是一個眾人已期待許久的時刻...
Louis, come on down!  Come down!
路易斯, 下來，快下來!
...could be rather historic.
...也有可能是極具歷史意義的一個時刻
And CNN can now project  that Barack Obama, 47 years old,
此刻，CNN基本可以推測出...
will become the President-Elect
現年47歲的巴拉克·奧巴馬
of the United States. We project...
會成為美國的總統當選人
If there is anyone out there
我們預計...
who still doubts that America  is a place where
那些對於....  「在美國任何事情都有可能發生」
all things are possible...
這一說法持懷疑態度的人...
...who still wonders if the dream of our  founders is alive in our time,
那些想知道我們先輩的夢想是否還存在的人
who still questions  the power of our democracy,
那些對我們的民主的力量心懷疑慮的人
tonight is your answer.
今晚，你將會得到回答
You must look  through their eyes...
你一定要通過他們的眼睛...
...see what it is that they want...
...看出他們在想什麼...
...see what it is that they need...
...看出他們需要什麼...
...anticipate...
...預測...
...bring a smile  to the principal's eyes.
...要讓你的服務對像露出笑容
Mr. Gaines.
蓋恩斯先生.
I'm Admiral Rochon, the chief usher.
我是阿德米拉爾.羅尚, 首席接待員.
- Nice to meet you, admiral.  - Pleasure's all mine, sir.
- 很高興見到你，阿德米拉爾.  - 無比榮幸，先生.
I just wanted to tell you  what an honor it is to meet you, sir.
我只是想告訴你能見到是多麼地榮幸，先生
The honor is mine.
這也是我的榮幸
The president's so excited  to meet with you.
總統非常期待能見到你.
Well...
噢...
...that's just fine, isn't it?
...那很好，不是嗎?
Let me show  you the way.
讓我為你帶路
I know the way.
我知道怎麼走.
The heart of the question is,
核心問題是,
whether all Americans  are to be afforded equal rights
是否所有的美國人都享有同等的權利
and equal opportunities.
和同等的就業機會
It is the effort of American  Negroes to secure for themselves
這是美國黑人為了保護  他們自己的權益...
the full blessings of American life.
和實現所謂的美國夢  所付出的努力和取得的成就
We will respond  with that timeless creed
我們將用那歷經時間考驗的
振奮我們精神的不朽信條回應他們:
Yes, we can.
是的，我們可以.
謹以這部影片獻給那些為了我們的自由  以及為了我們的公民權利而奮鬥的人們
本片涉及的歷史事件較多，如翻譯過程中存在疏漏，請多多諒解.  翻譯： @塔拉Tala
"I'll Close My Eyes"]